<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Meditations and disquisitions upon the creed. By Sr. Richard Baker Knight</title>
            <author>Baker, Richard, Sir, 1568-1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 211 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 125 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B510A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R231982</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900131</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900131</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170922</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170922)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2523:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Meditations and disquisitions upon the creed. By Sr. Richard Baker Knight</title>
                  <author>Baker, Richard, Sir, 1568-1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 239 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Iohn Davvson, for Francis Eglesfield at the Marigold in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sion College Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Creeds --  Protestant --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:1"/>
            <p>MEDITATIONS AND Diſquiſitions UPON THE CREED.</p>
            <p>BY S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. RICHARD BAKER <hi>Knight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by IOHN DAVVSON, for <hi>Francis Eglesſield</hi> at the <hi>Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gold</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:2"/>
            <head>TO THE GENEROVS, and worthy of much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, THOMAS BAKER of FREZINGFIELD, in the County of <hi>Suffolke,</hi> ESQVIRE.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt honoured Coſin:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is not the propinquity of bloud that is between us; It is not the great Obligation, in which I ſtand bound unto you; which yet, were cauſes of themſelves ſufficient: but it is the
<pb facs="tcp:170922:3"/>generouſneſſe of your minde, that make me deſirous, to conſecrate ſomething t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the memory of your Name; for thoug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your owne vertue will preſerve it ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently, yet my affection is not ſatisfied without bearing a part in it: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelfe but a whithered bough; may expreſſe my joy, in ſo flouriſhing branch of our Family, as your ſelfe is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And now, I know not whether I ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> account you young, in regard of your fer yeares: or Old, in regard of your muc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> experience: having ſpent Twelve year together, (a longer time then <hi>Vlyſſes</hi> in travelling over the moſt flouriſhing parts of <hi>Chriſtendome;</hi> where ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpent your time, in ſo noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> manner as Report delivers; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe but be returned home, <hi>Vir pau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> corum hominum;</hi> more compleat in good parts, then to have man Peeres. But to leave this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Having heretofore written <hi>Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:170922:3"/>upon the Lords Prayer:</hi> J have now adventured to doe the like upon the <hi>Creede;</hi> which <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> as J Dedicate to your Name; ſo my ſelfe, to your Service; and remaine</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Devoted to you, in all true Love and Affection,</salute>
               <signed>Richard Baker.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170922:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170922:6"/>
            <head>MEDITATIONS AND DISQVISITIONS <hi>Vpon the</hi> CREEDE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſeemes, that in laying the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of CHRISTS Church, where ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Proſelytes were to be admitted; this forme of <hi>Beliefe</hi> was firſt penned: to the end, that they which would be admitted into the Church, ſhould
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170922:7"/>firſt profeſſe the <hi>Beliefe</hi> of theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles; and theſe being beleeved, were thought to bee ſufficient, to ſhew the profeſſed Faith of an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe Chriſtian. But whether the Apoſtles themſelves were the Penners of it, as ſome have thought: or whether ſome other, out of the Apoſtles Doctrine, as the moſt conceive; is not much materiall to be examined: It is ſufficient for us, to know, that it is received by a Generall conſent of the whole Church.</p>
            <p>And although the Article of Chriſts <hi>Deſcending into Hell;</hi> hath for ſome time, in ſome Churches, not been received; yet this is no more then hath befallen ſome parts of the holy Scripture it ſelfe. For, the <hi>Epistle to the Hebrewes,</hi> and the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of Saint Iude,</hi> and ſome other, now generally received; have for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170922:7"/>ſome time, in ſome Churches, not beene admitted. But howſoever, former times, have had ſome ſcruple about this Article; yet wee muſt admit it now without ſcruple; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe we will make ſcruple alſo, to admit the Article of beleeving <hi>the Holy Catholike Church;</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Holy Catholike Church,</hi> hath long ſince admitted it into our <hi>Creede,</hi> as an Article neceſſary to be beleeved of every Chriſtian man.</p>
            <p>And it ſeems to containe a Brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate of thoſe things, which of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man are <hi>Credenda,</hi> to be Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: as the <hi>Ten Commandements,</hi> a Breviate of things that are <hi>Agenda,</hi> to be done; and the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> a Breviat of things, that are <hi>Oranda</hi> to be Prayed for: which Three, as they differ not much in the number of their Articles: ſo they ſeeme to have a great coherence, one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170922:8"/>For, what wee <hi>Beleeve,</hi> that wee have reaſon to doe; and what we are to doe; that we have juſt cauſe to Pray for, to be enabled to doe; That whilſt our Beleeving is manifeſted by our doing; and our doing proſpered by our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>The man of God may bee made perfect in every good worke.</hi> If wee ſhould doe as much as wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to doe; and not beleeve as much, as we are taught to beleeve; that doing would doe us little good: and if wee ſhould beleeve as much as wee are taught to beleeve, and not doe as much as wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to doe; that beleeving would doe us leſſe good: Then onely will the benefit of both of them accrew unto us, when <hi>Beleefe</hi> is joyned with <hi>Action;</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> with <hi>good Workes:</hi> without which conjunction, there may be Leaves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170922:8"/>but there will bee no Fruit. For if we ſhould do the Commandements, and not beleeve this <hi>Creed,</hi> our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion would want the <hi>Baſis;</hi> and if beleeve this <hi>Creede,</hi> and not doe the Commandements, it would want the <hi>Coronis.</hi> And ſo theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are the fundamentals, of that which is to be beleeved of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; but the fundamentals of that which is to be done of a Chriſtian, are the Commandements in the Law, and in the Goſpell. Both which Fundamentals muſt be joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, to make up the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of our ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And this ſumme or Breviate of beliefe, which wee call our <hi>Creede;</hi> conſiſts of two parts, <hi>Perſonae &amp; Res:</hi> Firſt, the Perſons in whom wee muſt beleeve; and then the things which we muſt beleeve. The perſons in whom to beleeve are
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170922:9"/>three; <hi>God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt: Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and one God; Bleſſed for ever.</hi> The things which we are to beleeve are five: of which the two firſt, which are, <hi>The holy Catholique Church, and the Communion of Saints,</hi> as they heere ſtand next to the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt:</hi> ſo moſt properly they relate to the <hi>Holy Ghoſt:</hi> He being the fountaine of Sanctification, of which theſe two are ſtreames. The next two, which are <hi>the Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and the Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> ſeeme properly to referre to God the Sonne: in whoſe merits, as Man, all ſinnes are forgiven: and by the power of whoſe Riſing, as God and man, ſhall be our Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. And then the laſt, which is <hi>the Life Everlaſting,</hi> moſt proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relates to God the Father: He being the Author of Life; <hi>In whom
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170922:9"/>we al live, &amp; move, and have our being, &amp; ſhal have our eternal being.</hi> And this is the Coherence, <hi>Perſonarum &amp; Reru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> of the Perſons in whom to beleeve, and of the Things, which we are to beleeve. If wee ſhould know in whom to beleeve, and not know what to beleeve; we ſhould want our leſſon: and if we ſhould know what to beleeve, and not know in whom to beleeve, we ſhould want our Teacher: and therefore to make both perfect, both are heere expreſt; and expreſt ſo punctually, that nothing can be added, either to make it plainer, or to make it fuller.</p>
            <p>And heere it may not be amiſſe, for the credit of our Creede; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we goe further) to ſhew that all the Articles of it, are contained in the holy Scripture; and to bring ſome place of Scripture, for a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimoniall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170922:10"/>of each of them: that it may appeare, wee ground not our Beliefe upon Quagmires of uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainetie, but that wee have firme ground to ſtand upon, and it will be a worke not long in doing. The firſt Article, is the ſubject of the whole Bible, all tending to make us beleeve in God. The next Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle is the ſubject of the whole Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, all tending to make us beleeve in Chriſt. The next two Articles, of Chriſts Conception and his Birth; are declared by the Angell to <hi>Joſeph: Feare not Joſeph, to take Mary thy wife; for that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in her, is of the Holy Ghoſt: and ſhe ſhall bring forth a Sonne, and thou ſhalt call his Name jeſus.</hi> Then the next Article of Chriſts ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring under <hi>Pontius Pilate;</hi> is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently teſtified in <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> who gave ſentence to have <hi>Barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170922:10"/>releaſed, and Chriſt to be ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged: and then his being Crucified, Dead, and Buryed; are for more ſurety recorded with their circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances: That he was Crucified be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene two Theeves; and when his Legges ſhould have beene broken, he was found to bee Dead before: and then was Buried, and laid in a Sepulchre, where never man had been laid before, by <hi>Joſeph of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mathea,</hi> as all the Evangeliſts teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. But now the Article of Chriſts <hi>Deſcending into Hell,</hi> makes us at a ſtand; For none of all the Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts bring Chriſt any further then his Grave; there they leave him, and ſay not a word more of him, till his Riſing from the Dead; that for any thing appeares yet, this Article is like to be loſt, for want of a Teſtimoniall. It may ſeeme indeed ſtrange, that this Article
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170922:11"/>ſhould be in the Creed, and not b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> found in the Goſpel; ſeeing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goſpell ſeemes to bee the ground from which the Creed is taken. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is it not, that the ground of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Creed is not onely the Goſpell: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the whole Scripture? For th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Goſpell ſeemes to deliver no mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt, then what was viſible, and done in his body: and leaſt wee ſhould bee doubtfull, what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of his Soule, when his body was dead; therefore this Article, <hi>[Hee deſcended into Hell]</hi> is added: For wee may obſerve that in theſe Articles concerning Chriſt; this word <hi>[Hee]</hi> perſonates three Eſtates, as when it is ſaid, <hi>Hee was Crucified, Dead, and Buried;</hi> here the Word, <hi>Hee,</hi> Intends but onely his Body; as when it is ſaid, <hi>Hee Deſcended into Hell,</hi> heere <hi>Hee,</hi> intends but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Soule; and when it is ſaid,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170922:11"/>
               <hi>He roſe againe from the Dead;</hi> heere the word <hi>Hee,</hi> intends both his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and Soule together; and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues in all the Articles following: <hi>He aſcended into Heaven, He ſitteth at the right hand of his Father, He ſhall come to Iudge the Quick and the Dead;</hi> ſtill the Word <hi>Hee,</hi> intends both his Body and Soule together. From whence wee may gather, how it is like to be with us alſo; that though our ſoules and bodies be parted for a time, yet when in the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they once meet againe, they ſhall never afterward be parted any more.</p>
            <p>But though this Article ſeeme to have no ground in the Evangeliſts; yet in the Apoſtles and Prophets it hath: at leſt the Prophet <hi>David</hi> long before had ſaid in the perſon of Chriſt: <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in Hell;</hi> by which it appeares
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170922:12"/>that his ſoule was in Hell: and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what time ſo fit for the being there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as while his Body was lying in the Grave? and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo ſeeme to ſay as much, where hee ſaith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>He Deſcended into the loweſt parts of the Earth:</hi> which muſt needes bee certainely a lower place then the Grave. And ſo between the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>David,</hi> and the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> we ſhall be able to make this Article, a good Teſtimoniall, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from the one, the Place; from the other, the Motion; <hi>David,</hi> naming <hi>Hell;</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the ſtop of this Article, wee come againe into the Roade: For the Article of Chriſts <hi>Riſing from the Dead;</hi> hath not onely the Voyces of all the Evangeliſts; but it hath a clowde of Witneſſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirming, <hi>that more
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170922:12"/>then five hundred brethren at once, ſaw him being Riſen from the dead.</hi> Then he next Articles, (whether two or one) of his <hi>Aſcending into heaven, and ſitting at the Right hand of God,</hi> are in ſuch manner teſtified by Saint <hi>Marke,</hi> that the words of the Creed are but the very Tranſcript of his Text. Then the Article of Chriſts comming to <hi>Iudge the Quick and the Dead,</hi> is Proclaimed as from Chriſt himſelfe; that it is Hee, which was ordained of God, to be Judge both of quicke and dead. And then the Article of <hi>Beleeving in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> is made good by Chriſts laſt charge to his Apoſtles: <hi>Goe teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> and in whoſe Name wee are Baptized, in Him certainly we have juſt cauſe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve. But then the Article of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170922:13"/>
               <hi>the Holy Catholique Church</hi> makes us at a ſtand againe; Fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what place of Holy Scripture ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bee brought for a Teſtimony, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Beleeving the Catholick Church:</hi> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſo much as the word <hi>Catholick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> is to be found in any place of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture. For though ſome E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of ſome Apoſtles, be Inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <hi>Catholicke,</hi> yet Inſcription of Epiſtles is no part of the Scripture, no more then part of the Epiſtles, But is it not? that though the word <hi>Catholicke</hi> be not directly expreſt, yet it may be directly inferr'd; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many places of Scripture binde us to Beleeve the Church, but no particular Church: and therefore the Catholicke, or Univerſall Church. Then the Article of the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> Is it not fully expreſt by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> where hee ſaith, <hi>There is one Body, and one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170922:13"/>one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſme, one God and Father of all; who is above all, and through all, and in us all.</hi> Then for the Article of <hi>Remiſsion of ſinnes,</hi> We have as many Teſtimonies of Scripture, as there are words: but it may bee Teſtimoniall enough which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> giveth; where he ſaith, <hi>The bloud of Jeſus Chriſt clenſeth us from all our ſinnes.</hi> Then the Article of the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> though it might paſſe under the Article of Chriſts Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, without any other Teſtimony; <hi>(For if Chriſt be riſen from the Dead, we alſo ſhall riſe from the Dead.)</hi> Yet it hath a Teſtimony by it ſelf, where it is ſaid, <hi>God that raiſed up Chriſt from the Dead, ſhall alſo quicken our mortall Bodies, by his Spirit that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in us.</hi> And laſtly, the Article of <hi>Everlaſting Life,</hi> is Teſtified by Saint <hi>John,</hi> as it were in Red Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170922:14"/>where hee ſaith, <hi>God ſo love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the World, that hee gave his onely b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gotten Sonne; that whoſoever beleeve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in him, ſhould not periſh but have li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Everlaſting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having ſhewed, that a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Articles are contained in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Scripture: It remaines to ſhew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what it is they containe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi>] Where, firſt it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, that as in ſaying the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prayer, we ſay, <hi>Our Father,</hi> taking others along with us, and not go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our ſelves alone: So in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Creede,</hi> why we doe not as well ſay, <hi>Wee Beleeve,</hi> that ſo wee may not goe alone, but take others along with us? Is it not that Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe is Perſonall; but Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Communion of Saints: Prayer proceeds from Charity, and therefore is Communicative; but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170922:14"/>Beliefe proceeds from Faith, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erefore is reſerved. Another may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ray for mee, but another cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eleeve for me, I muſt beleeve for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y ſelfe, another cannot: (I ſpeak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot of Infants, but of <hi>Adulti.</hi>) It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s not here, that <hi>Per alium</hi> is as good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Per ſe,</hi> and therefore no ſuch Tye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or ſaying <hi>Wee Beleeve,</hi> in making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Profeſſion; as for ſaying <hi>Our Father,</hi> in making that Prayer.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I Beleeve:</hi>] But when I ſay, <hi>I Beleeve:</hi> Doe I well conſider, what it is I ſay? a word indeed ſoone ſpoken, but not a worke ſo eaſily done; for, we muſt not thinke, to put it off with God, as he did with men, who ſaid, <hi>Iuravilingua, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem injuratam gero:</hi> I ſwore with my tongue, but I kept my heart un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne. For God is a ſearcher of the heart, and lookes after that; and as ſoone as wee ſay to him, <hi>I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170922:15"/>Beleeve,</hi> he ſeemes preſently to ſay to us; Then give me your heart, for unleſſe you give me your heart, I will never beleeve, you ſpeake as you meane. And thus my ſoule, thou ſeeſt, how deepely thou haſt engaged thy ſelfe, by ſaying, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> and yet thy engagement not ſo great, but thy undertaking is greater. For to Beleeve is no ſuch eaſie matter, as the World accounts it: It is indeed, more then of our ſelves we are able to doe; For it is a worke of Faith, and <hi>Faith is the gift of God;</hi> and ſo we undertake to doe that to God, which without Gods aſſiſtance we cannot doe; as though wee had Gods aſſiſtance at command; No my ſoule, but wee muſt bee faine to helpe our ſelves with ſaying, <hi>I beleeve, O God; helpe my unbeliefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why am I ſo forward to Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170922:15"/>and doe not rather make a ſtand, and doubt? Seeing doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is commonly ſafe; where cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulity runs headlong into danger? Is it not that Beleeving is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and hath reward; For <hi>Abraham beleeved, and it was counted to him for Righteouſneſſe;</hi> where Not-Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving is diſtruſtfull, and hath not ſo much as Hope: and againe, Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving may make me of the number of the Faithfull; where Not-Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving may make me an Infidell: and though Beleeving may have leſſe worldly providence; yet certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, It may have more ſpirituall wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, then Not-Beleeving: and theſe are Reaſons that make me ſo forward to Beleeve.</p>
            <p>But what reaſon can I have to make me beleeve; when I muſt not beleeve reaſon? No doubt in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the world; the Rule is good,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170922:16"/>to beleeve no more then wee ſee good reaſon for; and thereupon is the counſell given, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Becarefull to bee miſtruſtfull: but in matters Divine, and belonging to God, hee that beleeves no more then Reaſon warrants, may juſtly be ſaid, not to Beleeve at all; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Beliefe is a worke of Faith; and Faith properly beginnes not her worke, but when the Reaſon hath given over working.</p>
            <p>There ſeeme to bee many induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Beliefe, but ſpecially two: Firſt, the Teſtimony of the Senſe; For who will not beleeve that, which hee ſees with his eyes; but this beliefe will not ſerve the turne. For <hi>Faith is an evidence of things not ſeene;</hi> and therefore wee muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, though wee doe not ſee. Then the Teſtimony of Reaſon; for, who will not beleeve that, for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170922:16"/>which hee ſees apparent reaſon? but neither will this Beliefe ſerve the turne, for Faith is above Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and <hi>Niſi Credideritis, non Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligetis:</hi> Unleſſe yee Beleeve, yee ſhall not underſtand, and ſo Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe muſt not alwaies ſtay for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding; but we muſt be faine to have recourſe to this ſtil; <hi>I beleeve, O God, helpe my unbeliefe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beliefe, indeed, is two fold; <hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane</hi> and <hi>Divine:</hi> Humane Beliefe is alwaies grounded upon Senſe or Reaſon: but Divine Beliefe hath other grounds to ſtand upon; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ground of <hi>Abraham, Qui in ſpe contra ſpem credidit:</hi> Who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to hope Beleeved in hope: or the ground of thoſe whom Chriſt calls Bleſſed; <hi>Bleſſed are they that have not ſeene, and yet have beleeved:</hi> For, we muſt not alwaies looke for the favour of Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi> to bee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170922:17"/>allowed to put our hands into Chriſts ſides before wee beleeve; but we muſt ſometimes come with Faith, without the concurrence of eternall Evidence, and then indeed is Beliefe moſt kindly, when it ſtands not upon the Prop of Senſe and Reaſon: which may be prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratives to Beliefe, but it is Faith that gives the confirmation.</p>
            <p>And as there are certaine induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Beliefe; ſo there are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine properties in Beliefe. It muſt be ſteadfaſt without wavering, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured without doubting, confident without preſuming; but above all, it muſt bee rightly applyed; for without right application, Beliefe is no better then Infidelity: and then onely is Beliefe rightly apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when it is applyed to God: and this brings me to ſay, <hi>[I beleeve in God:]</hi> For now I am ſure, I take
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170922:17"/>my ayme right, and apply my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe to the right Object. If I ſhould apply it to any but God, it muſt be to ſome Creature; and ſeeing eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature is ſubject to a Higher Power, what hope could I have to Beleeve in ſuch a one, who muſt himſelfe Beleeve in another? But when I apply my Beliefe to God, not onely I may juſtly hope, but I may ſecurely be aſſured, ſeeing God is a Power Supreme, and hath no E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to conteſt with him, much leſſe any Superiour to controule him. If I ſhould Beleeve in man, I might feare that which <hi>David</hi> ſaith, that <hi>All men are lyers:</hi> but when <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in God,</hi> I am out of that feare, ſeeing <hi>God is the Truth it ſelfe, and cannot lye.</hi> If I ſhould Beleeve in Angels, I know the Angels did once fall, and what they did once, they might doe againe, if they were
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170922:18"/>not upheld by a ſtronger Power; and can it bee ſafe Beleeving in them, who ſtand by the power of another, and not by their owne? But when <hi>I beleeve in God,</hi> my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe is built upon a ſure Foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſeeing <hi>Heaven is Gods Throne, and the Earth his Foot-ſtoole:</hi> that he is neither capable of Riſing, nor ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to falling. <hi>David</hi> would not put his truſt in man, pronouncing him accurſed that ſhould doe it; and why ſhould I? <hi>Moſes</hi> would not truſt an Angell to be his guide, though God himſelfe offered him one; and why ſhould I? No, my ſoule, but <hi>Adhaerere Deo bonum est,</hi> It is good ſticking to God; and no aſſurance indeed of any good, but onely in ſticking to him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending wholly upon him.</p>
            <p>And as there are certaine pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of Beliefe, to make it bee
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170922:18"/>right; ſo there are certaine degrees of Beliefe, to make it perfect. The firſt Degree, is to Beleeve, <hi>There is a God;</hi> and this Degree is ſo ſenſible and plaine, that he muſt be a Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall foole that beleeves it not: as <hi>David</hi> calls him; <hi>The Foole hath ſaid in his heart, There is no God.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Degree, is to Beleeve him in all he ſaith, or promiſeth; which is in effect, but to account him an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle. Another Degree, is to beleeve him to be a Rewarder of them that ſerve him; an effect of his Juſtice: and all theſe Degrees of Beliefe may be in a man, and yet no true beleeving in God: For, theſe doe but amount to <hi>Credere Deum,</hi> or <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere Deo;</hi> which a man may doe as a ſtander by, and as onely a looker on; though he make himſelfe no party in the matter. The true Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in God indeed, is <hi>Credere
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170922:19"/>in Deum,</hi> to intereſt our ſelves in him, to depend wholly upon him, to put all our truſt and confidence in him; to account him not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly our Oracle to Direct us, but our Sanctuary to Protect us; to make him not onely our Hope, but our Aſſurance, and both in life and death, to ſay that to him, which Chriſt ſaid at his death: <hi>In manus tuas Domine, commendo ſpiritum meum,</hi> Into thy hands, O Lord, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſpirit.</p>
            <p>I therefore beleeve in God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not in Gods; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not in Gods, becauſe there are no Gods to beleeve in: For if there were more Gods then One, there ſhould be none at all, ſeeing it is againſt the nature of God to bee more then One. Neither indeed, will Time or Place allow any more. For of Place, it is true
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170922:19"/>which God ſaith of himſelfe; <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum &amp; Terram ego impleo,</hi> Heaven and Earth I fill: and if One God fill all places, what roome can there be for any other? And of Time, it is true alſo, that God is <hi>Primum Ens,</hi> the Firſt Being; but there can be but One Firſt, and therefore but One God. And as One multiplyed by One, can never make any more then One: ſo God being Unity it ſelfe, can never be multiplied into a number; but it is moſt true which the Jewes ſay of him: <hi>Hu a'chad ue aein ſhenì;</hi> He is One, and there is not a Second: and yet perhaps not true in their meaning: For they may meane it of the Perſons in the Deity; of which here is both a Second, and a Third, and yet all Three, but One God. And if there were more Gods then One, there could bee no Beliefe; at leaſt, but diſtracted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170922:20"/>Beliefe; and diſtraction is deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to beliefe: For if it be not Fixt and Intentive upon One and the ſame power ſtill, it may bee Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but it cannot be Beliefe.</p>
            <p>But what is God, or who is the Lord, that I ſhould beleeve in him? For to Beleeve in God, and not know what God is, were to Beleeve in I know not what, and were like to make but a blind Beliefe. Is it then, that there is ſomething which is ſeene by being inviſible, which is known by being Incomprehenſible: and that, my Soule is God? Or is it, there is ſomething, whoſe Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is every where, and Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence no where, whoſe Power is Infinite, and in whoſe hands are all the corners of the Earth, and that my Soule is God? Or is it, there is ſomething, which cannot be ſaid, It was; and yet hath alwaies been;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170922:20"/>Nor cannot be ſaid, It wil be, &amp; yet ſhal be for ever, and that my Soule is God? Or is it, ther is ſomthing, whoſe Being cannot be conceived, and yet whoſe Being onely is conceivable, which exceeds the Sun in brightnes, yet is no quality; the World in great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet is no quantity, and that, My Soule is God? But indeed God is He, who brought the Ten great Plagues upon <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for preſuming to aske this Queſtion. For who can be excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that takes not notice of his <hi>Being,</hi> who is the Author of al <hi>Being?</hi> Who can be excuſed, that knows not, who Hee is, that onely is? And therefore when <hi>Moſes</hi> asked God his Name, he anſwered, <hi>I am that I am:</hi> meaning, that his Being was his Name: For as a name is proper to the thing named, ſo Being is proper only to God: all other things rather ſeeme to be, then are: Or if they bee indeed, yet it
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170922:21"/>is but a Being which they have from him; ſeeing in Him, <hi>we all live, and move, and have our being.</hi> And this <hi>I am</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> is my <hi>I am too:</hi> For it is true, which God ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>Ego Deus, &amp; non mutor;</hi> I am God, and there is none to change for me; and therefore in Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving in this <hi>I am;</hi> I am, (I am ſure) in a a right Beliefe, which makes me to beginne my Creede with this, <hi>I beleeve in God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thought the Beliefe, no doubt, be true; Yet it is but a truth which Jewes and Turkes beleeve as well as we; For, they alſo Beleeve in God, and in one God; and ſhall a Chriſtians Belief go no further then theirs? Yes, my Soule; For, <hi>I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in God the Father,</hi> the firſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Trinity, and this, no Jew nor Turke beleeves. For they have alwaies ſtuck at One, and could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:170922:21"/>bee gotten to come to Three; when yet without knowing this Three, that One can never be true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowne. Although to ſay the truth, this Myſtery of Three in One, is a Truth not ſo much to be known, as to be Beleeved; For if it could be perfectly knowne, It would not perhaps bee ſo fit for a Creede, which conſiſts in Believing, as for ſome Art, that conſiſts in knowing. But though I cannot perfectly know this Myſtery, yet I Beleeve it; becauſe I ſubmit my underſtanding to Faith; which though I cannot make to goe along with Beliefe, as a Companion; yet I make it to wait upon Beliefe as a Servant: and this, neither Jew, nor Turke will be gotten to doe: They like not to make their Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a Servant; though they can be content to be ſervile themſelves,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170922:22"/>yet they will have their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be Free; and therefore what they comprehend not, they beleeve not; Fooliſh men, that would bring downe Heaven to Earth, and bound the profound Myſteries of God, within the ſhallow lymits of their owne braines.</p>
            <p>But what is meant by a Perſon in the Trinitie, which is neceſſary to be known; that when wee ſay, there bee Three perſons; It may not bee thought, we meane Three Gods. Indeed humane Infirmity is apt to fall into ſuch errour. Wee muſt therefore know, that a Perſon in the Trinity, is a Name of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, but not of Diverſitie: It makes <hi>Alium &amp; Alium,</hi> but not <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liud &amp; Aliud;</hi> and it is an Appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation proper onely to the nature of the Deity; and not to be found in any Creature whatſoever. The Perſon
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170922:22"/>of the Father is diſtinct from the Perſon of the Sonne; and the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Sonne from the Perſon of the Holy Ghoſt, but Diſtinct in Relation, not in Subſtance; and all Three Perſons are but One God. And to make it plainer, we may ſay, that God conſidered as Beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, is the Perſon of the Father; conſidered as Begotten, is the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Sonne; and conſidered as proceeding from the Father and the Sonne, is the Perſon of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt; In theſe onely diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; in all other points of Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, One. The Father is not more God then the Sonne; nor the Son then the Holy Ghoſt: They are Three in Subſiſtence, but one in Subſtance; the Subſiſtence makes the Trinitie; the Subſtance, the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; an Ineffable Myſtery; which we may Beleeve, but cannot Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170922:23"/>O my Soule, how much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re wee bound to God, for revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling this Myſtery of the Bleſſed Trinity to us; and more, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us capable to Beleeve it; For, as without revealing, wee ſhould never have knowne it: So with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Grace, wee could never have Beleeved it; But now by the Eye of Faith; and by the Light of Grace, we come to ſee, as it were a glympſe of that glorious Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring; when wee ſhall ſee God, not in <hi>Idaeas,</hi> repreſented by the Fancie; but in the miraculous Verity of his owne Being; which as none can ſee now and live; ſo there ſhall be then, no life, but in ſeeing it; no joy, but in beholding it.</p>
            <p>But though the Perſons in the Trinity, be all equall in Deity; yet not all Equall in all reſpects: For how then ſhould it be true; which
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170922:23"/>Chriſt ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>Pater ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor eſt me;</hi> The Father is greater then I: Not greater then Hee, onely as Man; For, this were no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; nor greater then He, as God: for this were no poſſible matter: but greater then He, as Sonne; for the Sonne is of the Father, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of None: and in that reſpect is greater then the Sonne; Not as God, but as Father; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the ſenſe, in which Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The Father is greater then I;</hi> in that ſenſe doe I place the Father firſt in my Creede, and ſay firſt, <hi>I Beleeve in God the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though I cannot apprehend, how God being but One, ſhould be Three; yet I beleeve it, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving it, I Adore it; and though I cannot apprehend, how <hi>[Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty]</hi> One ſhould be Almighty, where Three be Equall; yet I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170922:24"/>it, and beleeving it, I admire it. Indeed if God were not Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, he could not be God; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his power ſhould bee limited; and a limited Power, implies a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Power that limits it, which ſhould be God, rather then Hee; and therefore not Almighty, no God. And againe, if hee were not Almighty, our Beliefe in him might be fruſtrate: For his want of Might, might be in that, for which wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon him; and if no depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding upon him, then no beleeving in him neither; but now being God, and being Almighty: we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in him, not onely juſtly as God; but ſecurely, as Almighty: ſeeing whatſoever our want be; yet he being Almighty, can ſupply it; how great ſoever our Danger be, yet he being Almighty can De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend us: how ſtrong ſoever our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:170922:24"/>Enemies be, yet he being Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie can Protect us: and as wee are aſſured, that he can; ſo wee doubt not, but he will: ſeeing there is in him, no leſſe readineſſe to doe it, as being a Father; then Power to bee able to doe it, as being Almighty.</p>
            <p>Here the Atheiſt inferres, that God cannot truely be ſaid to bee <hi>Almighty,</hi> ſeeing there are many things which he cannot doe: as he cannot Dye; he cannot lye, he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny himſelfe; and if hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe theſe things, then he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe all things; and If hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe all things, then can hee not truely be ſaid to be <hi>Almighty.</hi> But who ſees not the groſeneſſe of this ſubtilty, ſeeing theve are not Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Power, but Infirmities; and not to be able to doe things, which it is not Ability to doe, but Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; what prejudice can this be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:170922:25"/>to Almightineſſe? And yet, it cannot ſo properly be ſaid of God neither, that hee is not able to doe theſe things, as that hee is able not to doe them; and ſo his not being able, is indeed an Ability, and an effect of Power; and therefore no cauſe for this to deny his Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe, but to affirme it rather.</p>
            <p>But what is more frequent with Heathen Writers, then to call their fained God <hi>Jupiter, Pater Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens,</hi> The Almighty Father: and what doe we then Beleeve more in this, then the Heathen doe? Wee therefore Adde: <hi>[Maker of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth;]</hi> and this no Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then man did ever beleeve: For ſome of them thought the World to be made by chance, and by the caſuall concourſe of <hi>Atomes.</hi> Some againe, thought it to bee Eternall, and not to have beene made at all:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170922:25"/>None of them ever aſcribed the making it to God, and therefore in our Creede we juſtly ſay, <hi>God the Father,</hi> as againſt the Jew and Turk; we ſay, <hi>Almighty,</hi> as againſt the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt;</hi> and we ſay, <hi>Maker of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth,</hi> as againſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
            <p>Indeed, nothing doth ſo mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly demonſtrate the Almighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>God,</hi> as the making of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth; becauſe hee made them when there was no matter to make them off: as it is ſaid, <hi>In the beginning, God made Heaven and Earth:</hi> and againe, <hi>In the beginning there was no Time;</hi> ſo before Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth, there was no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and to make them when there was no matter to make them off, was to make Something of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, the moſt abſolute Character of Almightineſſe that can bee. If
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170922:26"/>we ſhould ſay, Maker of Man and Beaſt: this would not ſerve to ſhew Almightineſſe, ſeeing there was matter, whereof they were made, for of Earth they were made both: But to ſay, <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth,</hi> is ſo evident an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Almightineſſe, that the Heathen themſelves could not chuſe but have acknowledged it: if they had not beene blinded with their falſe Principle, <hi>Ex Nihilo Nihil fit,</hi> of Nothing is made Nothing: a Principle, true indeed in relation to Nature, but falſe in relation to the Power of God, to whom, Nothing is as much as Matter, and Matter is no more then Nothing, ſeeing Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Nothing are all One to him.</p>
            <p>Neither yet is the Almightineſſe of God, more evidently ſeene in making the Heaven and the Earth
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170922:26"/>of Nothing, ſo contrary to the courſe of Nature; then it is ſeene in making them in a Frame, ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the courſe of Art: For where in all Artificial Buildings, the Roofe is alwaies contiguous, by mediate Joynts unto the Foundation. In this Frame, the Heaven which is the Roofe, is ſo farre from being conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guous to the Earth, that there is <hi>Magnum Inane,</hi> an Infinite extenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of empty Ayre betweene them. And where the Foundation in all Artificiall Structures, is alwaies laid upon firme ground, that it may ſuſtaine and beare it up: In this Frame, the Earth which is the Foundation, is laid upon nothing but thinne Ayre, ſo farre from any firmeneſſe, that it is alwaies in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and yet the Earth it ſelfe ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver moving. And if wee take the Sea, as a part of the Earths Globe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170922:27"/>Is there not as great a wonder in that alſo: ſeeing, where all liquid things doe naturally overflow all that is under them; here the liquid Sea is above the Earth, and yet overflowes it not. And now ſtand and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, all yee Heathen, acknowledge and admire the <hi>Almightineſſe of God, that is the Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is God the Father the onely <hi>Maker of Heaven and Earth.</hi> Is it not ſaid in Saint <hi>John: In the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was the Word, and the Word was with God, and the Word was God: all things were made by him, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out him was nothing made that was made.</hi> It is true indeed, all <hi>Opera ad Extra,</hi> all exteriour works are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all the Perſons in the Deity: but yet in ſome reſpects, they are ſometimes appropriated more to One then to another: heere there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in ſpeaking of Heaven and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170922:27"/>Earth; the Originall of Creatures: the making them is juſtly attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>God the Father,</hi> the originall Creator: for otherwiſe it is ſo true, that they all had a hand in making them; that it is ſaid of the Holy Ghoſt alſo, that <hi>Spiritus Dei Incubabat,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>God</hi> moved upon the face of the waters, and what was this but a Fomenting the worke of the Father and the Sonne, by the Bond of Concord: the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per worke of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>From hence we may learne, that the World hath not been from Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting: For if <hi>God be Maker of Heaven and Earth,</hi> then Heaven and Earth were made; and if made, then made in time: and if made in time, then there was a time when they were not made. But how could this bee, ſeeing there was no time, till they were made. But yet there was a ſpace
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:170922:28"/>of Duration, and that ſpace had beene from Everlaſting: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Everlaſting, how could it ever come to have an ende? and an End it muſt have, before Time could come to have a Beginning. <hi>O my Soule, Theſe are no Thoughts for thee, thy wings are too weake to fly ſo high a pitch: Thy Plummets are too ſhort, to ſound ſo great a depth: It may bee ſufficient for thee to know, that although, God made not the World from Everlaſting; yet hee made it then when from Everlaſting hee had Decreed to make it: but how hee brought Time out of Eternity is a myſtery, thou ſhalt never attaine to know, till thou come thy ſelfe to attaine Eternity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre wee are brought by Belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">And in his onely Sonne, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</note> but ſeeing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:170922:28"/>is a Relative: and every Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, imples a Correlative, and the Correlative to Father is Sonne, this brings my Beliefe a degree further; to Beleeve <hi>in his onely Sonne, Jeſus Chriſt our Lord:</hi> Not his Sonne by Adoption, as we are; nor his Son by Creation and Grace, as Angels are: but his Sonne by Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as onely himſelfe is; and ſuch a Sonne, as the Father Proclaimes to be His; and tels the day when he begot him; <hi>Hodie genui te,</hi> This day have I begotten thee. But what day was this day? Not ſuch a day, as our dayes are, which follow one after another: but a day, in which there is nothing Before nor after; but the Paſt and the Preſent are both at once; the Paſt, in <hi>Genui;</hi> the Preſent, in <hi>Hodie:</hi> indeed a day, Not of Time, but of Eternity; which makes him Co-eternall with
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170922:29"/>his Father, One good degree of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality: And as the day of his Begetting is not like ours: So nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is the manner of his Begetting like ours; For where our Beget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is a Third from Two; his Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting is a Second from One, and therefore muſt needs bee of One ſubſtance Both, and this makes him Conſubſtantiall with the Father: another good degree of Equality: which kind of Begetting though it exceede our capacity, yet it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds not our Beliefe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, though our Inquiſitive Thoughts would faine bee making further <hi>Querees</hi> about it, yet Faith makes us contented to take this for an Anſwer: <hi>Generationem ejus quis enarrabit? Who ſhall declare his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration?</hi> If then the day of his Begetting, make him Co-eternall with the Father, and the manner of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170922:29"/>his Begetting, make him Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall with the Father: have we not as good ground, for our Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him, as in the Father? And though it may be thought, no Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is left for the Sonne, the Father being Almighty: yet all Power is given to the Sonne, both in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth: for though the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee Almighty, yet Almighty but as God; and therefore Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty as due to the Sonne, who is God with the Father: and as juſt cauſe wee have to ſay to the Sonne, as to the Father, <hi>Wee praiſe thee O God, wee knowledge thee to bee the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how can the Sonne that is begotten, be Co-eternall with the Father who Begets? Seeing that which Begets, is alwaies before that which is Begotten? But is not this a fallacie? They being Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170922:30"/>Seeing nothing can Beget, but there muſt bee ſomething Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten: there cannot bee a Father, till there bee a Sonne: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the Father bee from Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, the Sonne alſo is from E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, and ſo are Co-eternall.</p>
            <p>But though the Sonne may bee Co-eternall with the Father; yet how can he be Conſubſtantiall with the Father? Seeing the Subſtance of every thing is proper to it ſelfe, and cannot bee communicated to another. This indeed were true, if the Father and the Sonne, were <hi>Aliud &amp; Aliud,</hi> and not onely <hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp; Alius;</hi> but now being Both One God, and onely Two Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: Seeing the difference of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons makes no difference of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; they remaine of One Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance Both, and ſo are Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170922:30"/>
            <p>Thus farre reacheth our Beliefe in the Divinity of the Son; but ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing we beleeve him to be both per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>God</hi> and perfect <hi>Man,</hi> this leades our Beliefe a degree further: <hi>To Beleeve in Jeſus Chriſt our Lord;</hi> Termes belonging to his Humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <hi>Jeſus,</hi> a Name given him by an Angel, when hee was yet in his Mothers womb; <hi>Becauſe hee ſhould ſave his people from their ſinnes: Chriſt,</hi> a Name given him from his Office, <hi>As being a Prieſt after the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Melchiſedech, annointed with the oyle of gladneſſe above his fellowes: Lord,</hi> a Name given him from his Dominion, <hi>For of his Kingdome there ſhall be no end.</hi> O Bleſſed Son of God, Let mee enjoy the benefit of thy Name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> that I may bee ſaved from my ſinnes: Let me enjoy the benefit of thy Name <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that I may bee partaker of the oyle of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170922:31"/>gladneſſe, with which thou wert Annointed. Let me enjoy the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of thy being my <hi>Lord;</hi> that being thy Servant, I may have thy Protection, and Thou my Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>But how happens it, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid in the beginning of my Creede; <hi>I Beleeve:</hi> I now come to ſay, <hi>Our Lord:</hi> and ſo where I went ſingle out; am now ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fallen into company: It is true indeed; I ſayd, <hi>I Beleeve,</hi> when I ſpake but as regarding my owne perſon; but now that I ſpeake, as regarding the Communion of Saints; I ſay, <hi>Our Lord.</hi> For, though Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaid, <hi>My God, and my Lord,</hi> as though hee would claime CHRIST wholly to himſelfe; yet that ſeemes ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken but in paſſion, and to make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for his former doubting.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170922:31"/>
            <p>But now that I ſpeak deliberatly; I can ſay no leſſe, then <hi>Our Lord;</hi> ſeeing as Chriſt is a Saviour not of me onely, but of all mankinde; ſo he is the Lord, not of me onely, but of all that ſerve him: and thus Chriſt is that Lord, in whom is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded the Riddle of <hi>David, The Lord ſaid unto my Lord;</hi> For if hee be <hi>Davids</hi> Lord, how is hee his Sonne? and if he bee his Sonne, how is he his Lord? Indeed Both; his Son as concerning the Fleſh, but his Lord concerning Divine Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: and if <hi>Davids</hi> Lord, then alſo of us all; ſeeing of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as there ſhall be no End; ſo neither is there any limitation; but it is as Univerſall, as Eternall.</p>
            <p>But though Chriſt bee the Sonne of <hi>God,</hi> by Generation, concerning his Divinity; yet not by generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on concerning his Humanity: but
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170922:32"/>I Beleeve,
<note place="margin">Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt.</note> 
               <hi>He was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Not that the Holy Ghoſt was his Father: For the Father contributes matter to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Sonne: but the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> contributes no matter to the being of Chriſt; doth nothing to <hi>ſupple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re vicem Patris,</hi> but onely to be <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementum Matris;</hi> Indeed a Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which paſſeth our conceiving: That if <hi>Mary</hi> doubted, how this ſhould be, ſeeing ſhe knew not man; we as well may doubt it, ſeeing we know not the manner, nor ever can know it: but the anſwer which the Angels gave to ſatisfie <hi>Mary,</hi> muſt ſerve alſo to ſatisfie us: <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſhall come upon thee: and the Power of the Higheſt ſhall overſhadow thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here now comes in, the great Myſtery of the Incarnation of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170922:32"/>the Sonne of God; to the Jewes a Scandall, and a ſtumbling Blocke to the Gentiles; and yet the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, not more hard to Beleeve, then neceſſary to be Beleeved: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo neceſſary, that there is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly no Antichriſtian, but hee that denyes it, as Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith; <hi>Who is the Antichriſt, but hee that denies Chriſt to be come in the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why was it neceſſary that the Sonne of God ſhould bee Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate? Indeed for many great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: For his being Incarnate, makes him the more to commiſerate our infirmities; his being Incarnate brings our Fleſh againe within the Verge of Sanctification: but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his being Incarnate makes him fit to be a Mediator betweene God and us: makes him fit to bee a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice for our ſins; and if it were not for his being Incarnate, we ſhould
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170922:33"/>never have Acceſſe to the Throne of God. O bleſſed Ieſus, what Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite benefits doe we receive by thy being Incarnate; but what benefit doſt thou receive by it thy ſelfe? Alas, onely to make a purchaſe of a number of ungratefull wretches; who little conſider, what great things thou haſt done for us: little conſider, what great ſufferings thou haſt endured for us; little conſider thy Love, thy Patience, thy Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, in taking our Fleſh upon thee; when yet but for thy ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it upon thee, our Fleſh ſhould never have come to Inherit Heaven.</p>
            <p>But why was the Sonne Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and not as well the Father, or the Holy Ghoſt? Indeede for juſt cauſe: For, it was not fit the Father ſhould bee Incarnate; becauſe the Incarnation was to pacifie the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170922:33"/>Nor was it not fit the Holy Ghoſt ſhould be Incarnate; becauſe the Incarnation was to be the worke of the Holy Ghoſt: onely the Son was fit to bee Incarnate; becauſe it was congruous that being the Sonne in the Trinitie, hee ſhould alſo bee the Sonne of the Woman; So to make us the Sonnes of God, without remooving out of his Spheare of Sonne-ſhip at all.</p>
            <p>And heere begins the difference betweene the Humane nature of Chriſt and Ours. For wee are all of us conceived in ſinne: as <hi>David</hi> ſaith of himſelfe, <hi>That he was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in ſinne:</hi> and as <hi>David,</hi> ſo wee all; but Chriſt was conceived by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and therefore with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne. And as all the paſſages of our time eſteemed, are like our Beginning: Conceived in ſinne, Borne in ſinne, Living in ſinne, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170922:34"/>Dying in ſinne: So all the paſſages of Chriſts time afterward, are like his Beginning: Conceived without ſinne, Borne without ſinne, Living without ſinne, and Dying without ſinne; by which it was wrought, that though he tooke upon him our whole nature, &amp; became in al things like to us; yet ſinne was excepted.</p>
            <p>And that which was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, did not prove (we may be ſure) a falſe conception; but proſpered and proceeded to a perfect Birth; &amp; therfore, as I Beleeve, <hi>he was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt:</hi> So, I Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Borne of the Virgine</hi> MARIE.</note> hee was <hi>Borne of the Virgin Mary;</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived altogether Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturally in her, but borne for the moſt part Naturally of her; was nouriſhed in her Wombe; lay nine moneths encloſed in her Wombe; came forth of her Wombe
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:170922:34"/>after the courſe of Nature, and yet Borne Supernaturally of her too; Supernaturally, as of a Virgine, though naturally as of a Woman: For he was <hi>Natus ex Virgine, Borne of a Virgine:</hi> So he was <hi>Factus ex muliere, made of a Woman;</hi> Not made in her, but made of her; was Fleſh of her Fleſh, and Bone of her Bone, as truly as <hi>Eve</hi> of <hi>Adams.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It may well bee ſaid; hee was Borne Supernaturally of her: For who ever heard of ſuch a thing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; a Virgine to bee the mother of a Childe? But though it were never heard off before, that ſuch a thing was; Yet it was heard before that ſuch a thing ſhould bee: For the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> long before had foretold, <hi>A Virgin ſhall be with Childe, and ſhall bring forth a Sonne:</hi> and what marvell, if there never were ſuch a Mother before, when there
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170922:35"/>never was ſuch a Childe before? For this is that Childe, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>This day is borne to you a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, which is Chriſt the Lord:</hi> and a Saviour of whom? No leſſe then of all mankinde; and this no leſſe ſtrange then his Birth: A child to be a Saviour of men; and One Childe of all mankinde, fully as ſtrange, as to be Borne of a Virgin; Indeed ſtrange Both, or rather Wonderfull Both; yet as ſtrange or wonderfull as they Both are; we Beleeve them Both, though but One of them be delivered heere for an Article of our Creede.</p>
            <p>It is Recorded of many, that they were Sanctified in their Mothers Wombe; as amongſt others, of <hi>Jeremy</hi> the Prophet, but never Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded of any, that he was Concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the Holy Ghoſt, but onely of Chriſt; and between being San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified:
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170922:35"/>and being conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, there is very great oddes: For to be Sanctified, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have a meaſure of Holineſſe; but to bee conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, is to have the whole Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance made Holy: To be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, is onely to have Grace infuſed in the Soule; but to be conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, is to have both Body and Soule bee altogether Grace it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But though Chriſt were concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved without ſinne, becauſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Holy Ghoſt; yet how could hee bee borne without ſinne, being borne of a ſinnefull woman? For though <hi>Mary</hi> were a Virgin, yet, no doubt, ſhee was a ſinner; For why elſe ſhould ſhe need a Saviour? as ſhee ſaith her ſelfe, <hi>My ſpirit rejoyceth in God my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour:</hi> and could Chriſt take fleſh
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:170922:36"/>of a ſinner, and not with that fleſh take ſinne? But is it not that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt is the Sanctifier, and could aſwell ſanctifie the Fleſh it ſelfe, as the motions of the Fleſh: and therefore make him as well borne without ſinne, as conceived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne: ſinne not being able to enter, where the Holy Ghoſt keeps poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>But why is there mention made of the Virgin <hi>Mary?</hi> Is it not enough to beleeve that Chriſt was borne of a Virgin: but there muſt be added, the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> Indeed it is added very juſtly; for by this it appeares, that Chriſt was Deſcended of the Lynage of <hi>David,</hi> (his Mother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ſame Lynage) as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets had foretold, the true Chriſt ſhould bee, and this is no ſmall ſtrengthening to our Beliefe, that Chriſt is the true Meſſias.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170922:36"/>
            <p>But how is it like, that <hi>Mary</hi> was a Virgine, when ſhee had a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band? at leaſt, how can wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve ſhee was a Virgin, when ſhee had a Child? Is it not that her Marriage was Inchoate indeed, but not Conſummate; ſhee was <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſata,</hi> but not <hi>Nupta;</hi> ſhee was not Married. And therefore Eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that there might bee One to take care of her, and her Childe when it ſhould be borne.</p>
            <p>But why ſhould her Husband take care of a Childe that was none of his owne? might he not rather juſtly ſuſpect her, to have played falſe with him, and therefore ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put her to ſhame, at leaſt put her from him, then to take her to him? It is indeed a hard matter to make one beleeve, that a woman ſhould have a Childe, and not accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with man: but as it was the
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170922:37"/>Holy Ghoſt, that wrought the conception of Chriſt in his Mothers Wombe; ſo it was the Holy Ghoſt that wrought this Beliefe in the minde of her husband <hi>Joſeph,</hi> that the Angell told him true, when he ſaid unto him; <hi>Feare not Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph to take Mary thy wife: For that which is conceived in her, is of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though ſhee were the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Childe, yet ſhe continued a Virgin ſtill; For neither the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of Chriſt, nor the Birth of Chriſt, did abrogate her Virgini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; but rather made her, if not a more Virgin; at leaſt, a pure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin then ſhee was before. For ſuch is the purity of Chriſts Body, that it makes all paſſages the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urer by which it paſſeth: and therefore it may bee piouſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beleeved, and without <hi>Hyperbole,</hi> that as ſhe was
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170922:37"/>
               <hi>Virgo ante partum,</hi> ſo ſhee was <hi>Virgo in partu,</hi> and <hi>Virgo poſt partum;</hi> a Virgin before the Birth, and in the Birth, and after the Birth; for though ſhee had Purification, yet that perhaps, was but as Chriſt had Baptiſme, to fulfill all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>And as Chriſt was conceived of <hi>Mary</hi> without ſinne; ſo <hi>Mary</hi> was Delivered of Chriſt without paine; for it was but juſt, that ſhe who brought him forth, that Freed mankind from the generall Curſe, ſhould in bringing him forth, bee Freed her ſelfe, from the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Curſe laid upon Woman-kind; which was, <hi>That in ſorrow they ſhould bring forth Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if Jeſus Chriſt were Borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary:</hi> how could he be the Sonne of the Virgin, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told by the Prophet <hi>Eſay,</hi> For the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170922:38"/>Sonne of that Virgin, was to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Immanuell,</hi> and not <hi>Jeſus:</hi> where this Sonne of the Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> was called <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and not <hi>Immanuell?</hi> But is it not, that <hi>Immanuell</hi> was not properly meant a Name of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation but of Act; and then was the Name Acted, when the Sonne of God tooke Fleſh, and was Incarnate: For being the Son of God, and taking our nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, he was God with us; and to be God with Us, was to be <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bleſſed <hi>Marie!</hi> what Tongue can expreſſe thy Happineſſe in thy ſelfe! thy glory in the world! to have thy Body nine moneths toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, be made a Heaven for the Son of God to dwell in! to have thy Wombe bee the ſacred Bed for the Holy Ghoſt to overſhadow! and more then both theſe, to have the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170922:38"/>Sonne of God to bee thy Sonne; and take Fleſh of thy Fleſh, and Bone of thy Bone; that all our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitie now to Heaven, muſt be attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to thee; that our fleſh which was never before without ſinne, is now made as pure, as when it was firſt made, muſt bee attributed to thee; and more then Both theſe; that our Fleſh is now exalted up to Heaven, muſt bee attributed to thee; that Chriſt ſitteth at the Right hand of his Father, to bee our Advocate, muſt be attributed to thee; and therefore all Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations ſhall juſtly call thee Bleſſed; juſtly thou mayeſt ſay, <hi>Thy Soule doth magnifie the Lord, and thy Spirit rejoyceth in God thy Saviour:</hi> For if ever Soule had cauſe to Magnifie the Lord; If ever Spirit had cauſe to rejoyce in God: It is Thine, It is Thine, moſt Bleſſed, moſt Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170922:39"/>and moſt to bee Admired <hi>Marie.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suffered under Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After we have Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved that <hi>Chriſt was Borne of the Virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:</hi> It followes next, that we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <hi>Hee ſuffered under Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late.</hi> But what? Suffered as ſoone as hee was borne? Indeed, as all of us beginne our life with Crying, which is an effect of Suffering; and bring this <hi>Omen</hi> with us into the world, of the miſeries that are to follow: So Chriſt was more like to doe it then any other, who was <hi>Vir Dolorum,</hi> a man of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes all his life long: but yet this is not the ſuffering that is here meant: For the ſuffering heere ſpoken of, was under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> which was not till many yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time of Chriſts birth. Was it then, that hee was ſmitten and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170922:39"/>buffeted, had a Crown of Thornes platted upon his Head, was mocked and ſcourged under <hi>Pontius Pilate?</hi> Great ſuffrings all; yet neither were theſe the Suffering that is heere meant: but as we uſe to ſay, when men are Executed, and put to death, that then they ſuffer: ſo the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring here meant, was his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and putting to Death; as Chriſt himſelfe calleth it, where he ſaith, <hi>I have deſired to eate this Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over with you before I ſuffer:</hi> which was done alſo under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> at that time Governour for the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes</hi> in <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though it bee neceſſary to beleeve that Chriſt ſuffered; yet why is it neceſſary to beleeve that he ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate?</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, becauſe there were many af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards that tooke upon them to be Chriſt; as Chriſt had fore-told,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170922:40"/>
               <hi>that many ſhould come in his Name, ſaying, I am Chriſt:</hi> But wee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge none of them to be the true Chriſt, but Him onely that ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have here an Example what little good there is in good Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, if they bee not followed home to their full period; for a good Intention in <hi>Pilate,</hi> for want of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing, coſt Chriſt a ſcourging more then otherwiſe, perhaps, hee ſhould have had; for out of a deſire to ſave his life, he cauſed him to bee ſcourged; hoping, in a good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it would have paſſed with the Jewes for a ſatisfying puniſhment: but when his ſcourging would not ſerve their turnes, nor pacifie their malice; he then left purſuing his good intention, and delivered him into their hands to be put to death. Unhappy <hi>Pilate!</hi> that ſeeking to doe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170922:40"/>him good, didſt him hurt; and thinking to ſave his life, didſt adde a ſcourging to his death. What ill lucke hadſt thou to bee a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour at this time, thereby to be made a Miniſter of ſo fowle a Fact? What ill hap hadſt thou that hee ſhould ſuffer under thee, who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for thee? Yet when thou hadſt ſhed his bloud, and that hee had ſuffered under thee; If thou hadſt made good uſe of ſhedding it, or good uſe of his ſuffering; it might perhaps have beene happy for thee; but to ſhed his bloud, and then to waſh thy hands in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: as though water could clenſe the guiltineſſe of blood, or as though thy hands could make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends for the fault of thy tongue: This, if leſſe impiouſly done, was yet more fooliſhly done, then that thou didſt before.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170922:41"/>
            <p>But, O my Soule, what a ſudden change is this? Wee have hitherto thought, that the time was now come of our long deſired expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: His being <hi>Conceived of the Holy Ghoſt, and borne of the Virgine Mary;</hi> ſeemed certaine ſignes unto us of our expected <hi>Meſsias:</hi> but now his ſuffering under <hi>Pontius Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> puts us cleane out of heart: and takes away al hope, that this can poſſibly be the Meſſias we expect. But do we forget, that the Prophet which told us; <hi>A Virgin ſhall bee with Childe: and ſhall bring forth a Sonne;</hi> the ſame Prophet tels us alſo; that <hi>He ſhould beare our Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities; and by his ſtripes we ſhould bee healed:</hi> Let theſe then bee laid to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and it will bee found, that his ſuffering, is as true a ſigne of his being the true <hi>Meſsias</hi> as either his Birth, or his Conception.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170922:41"/>
            <p>But how happens this great gap to be in our Creed, betweene the Birth, and the Suffering of Chriſt? Is there nothing to be beleeved of Chriſt; from the time he was borne, till the time he ſuffered under <hi>Pontius Pilate?</hi> which was more then thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares? If there be, why is it not here delivered? No doubt, there are many memorable things of Chriſt, between his Birth and his Death, and moſt worthy of our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving; as, that he was Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed the Eighth day; that he was worſhipped of the Wiſe men of the Eaſt; that at Twelve yeares old, he Diſputed in the Temple with the Doctors; that at Thirty yeares old, hee was Baptized of <hi>John</hi> in Jorden; that preſently after, he was led into the Wilderneſſe, to bee Tempted of the Devill; that Hee turned Water into Wine at a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170922:42"/>in <hi>Canaa;</hi> and many other moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> memorable things, but are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in this our Creede; becauſe no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Works efficient of our ſalvation For without any of theſe, he migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> have been our perfect Saviour: bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not ſo, without theſe expreſt in ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Creed: For if he had not taken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him our fleſh, which was his being borne of the Virgin <hi>Mary;</hi> and if he had not dyed for our ſinnes, which was his ſuffering under <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Pilate:</hi> and if he had not riſen againe from the Dead, and Aſcended into heaven; neither could we have had any Salvation by him; neither could hee have beene a Saviour to us; and therefore, theſe onely are expreſt in our Creed, and not the other; though the other no leſſe memorable then theſe, and as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy otherwiſe of our Beliefe.</p>
            <p>Or is it, that the Articles delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170922:42"/>here concerning Chriſt; are all of them in oppoſition to ſome He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie; from which in this Creed, we profeſſe our ſelves to be free? as, <hi>Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Hereſie of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dianitae;</hi> who held that Chriſt took fleſh from the Elements; and to the Elements, at his Riſing, reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored it againe. <hi>Borne of the Virgin Mary;</hi> in oppoſition to the Hereſie of <hi>Valentinus;</hi> who held that <hi>Chriſt</hi> tooke not fleſh of the Virgin; but onely paſſed through her Body, as Water through a Pipe. <hi>Suffered under Pontius Pilate,</hi> in oppoſition to the Hereſie of <hi>Cerdonius;</hi> who held, that Chriſts Body was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſible, and not ſubject to payne, but in appearance. <hi>Crucified,</hi> in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the Hereſie of <hi>Baſilides;</hi> who held that Chriſt himſelfe was was not Crucified, but <hi>Simon</hi> of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170922:43"/>
               <hi>Cyrene,</hi> wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e his Croſſe. <hi>Was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n oppoſition to the Hereſie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>chees;</hi> who held that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed not, but onely made a ſhew of D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing. <hi>Deſcended into Hell,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, whom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, to deny his deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into Hell <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe againe from the Dea;</hi> in oppoſition to the Hereſie of <hi>Cerintius,</hi> who held, that Chriſt is not yet riſen, but that he ſhall riſe hereafter. <hi>The third Day;</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the Hereſie of the <hi>Arme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> who held, that Chriſt roſe on the Sabbath day; and ſo on the Second Day, and not on the Third. <hi>Aſcended into Heaven;</hi> in oppoſition to the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſie of thoſe; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſaid, <hi>In Sole poſuit Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lum ſuum:</hi> were therefore of opinion, that hee went no higher then the Sunne. <hi>Shall come to Judge the Quicke and the Dead;</hi> in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170922:43"/>to the Hereſie of thoſe; who held, that there ſhall bee no Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Judgement, but every one to bee Judged at the time of his death, and not otherwiſe. And this perhaps might be a reaſon, why onely theſe Articles are delivered in our Creede, concerning Chriſt; though in other reſpects, many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might aſwell have been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and as well Beleeved.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Crucified,]</hi> But now wee are come to the ſuffering of Chriſt, and who can chuſe but ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in comming to it? For what was his ſuffering, but his putting to death? And to what Death; but the moſt painefell, and the moſt Ignominious death of all, the death of the Croſſe? <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> when in <hi>Herods</hi> diſpleaſure he was put to death; had yet a faire death; was onely Beheaded; a kind of death
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170922:44"/>that ſeemes to hold good quarte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with a Delinquent; no Terrour no Ignominy, no Lingring; as ſoot ended, as begunne; and in which the Senſe hath no leiſure to feele Paine; but the death of the Croſſe which Chriſt ſuffered, had in it all the parts of a cruell death; painefull and lingring: and which, to a generous minde, is more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous then both theſe; full of Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominy and Shame; and that, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing might bee wanting to the meaſure of the Ignominie, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified betweene two Malefactors; and to increaſe the Ignominy yet more, put in the midſt, as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Malefactor of all the three.</p>
            <p>And what was it to bee Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied? What, alas! but to have his Handes and his Feet nayled to the Croſſe, and there left hanging till hee ſhould bee dead; which
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170922:44"/>could not chuſe, but bee a long time, there being nothing to cauſe his death, but Paine and Bleeding; and Paine, though intollerable, is ſeldome deadly; Bleading though immeaſurably, is oftentimes health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
            <p>But how then happened it, that with being nayled onely to the Croſſe, he ſhould be dead ſo ſoone? For after ſix houres he gave up the Ghoſt. No doubt, it made him ſhed blood in abundance; and therefore, in that ſpace of time, he might well bleed to death. But ſo did the two Malefactors, who yet lived a longer time: was it then, that his death was haſtened, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a Speare thruſt into his ſide? But that was not done, till after hee was dead. Although one <hi>Peter Iohn</hi> an Hereticke, would needes, againſt plaineteſtimony of Scripture, main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170922:45"/>this Opinion, that it was done while hee was yet alive. Was i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> then perhaps, that his Faſting, and Watching, and Scourging the night before, had ſo exceedingly weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him; that he that could beare the burthen of our ſinne, yet could not heare the burthen of his Croſſe, but was faine to have <hi>Symon of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rene</hi> to beare it for him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was little better then dead al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Or, if theſe were not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to haſten his death; was it not perhaps, his own doing; who had power to lay downe his life, and to take it up againe at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and therefore dyed the ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, that it might be verified, which was Propheſied: <hi>There ſhall not a bone of him bee broken.</hi> For, if hee had not dyed when hee did, his legges ſhould have beene broken, as the two Malefactors were to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170922:45"/>their death, that they might be dead before the Sabbath. O deare Jeſus, what ſuch haſte was there for thy death, who onely wert wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy never to dye? but that by thy death thou haſt given us life; though all our lives were not worth the haſtening it; but that thy infinite love never thought it to be haſte enough.</p>
            <p>It is an olde Hereſie of ſome; that Chriſt himſelfe was not Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, but <hi>Symon of Cyrene</hi> in his ſtead; but the Temple and the Sunne make this knowne to bee a Fable. For would the Temple have rent in twaine? Would the Sunne have beene darkened ſo long toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for <hi>Symon of Cyrene?</hi> No a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, too true it is, that Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was Crucified; and woe to us that true it is; and yet more woe to us, if it were not true; but woe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170922:46"/>of all Woes, that true it is; in that for us, and for our ſinnes, it was that he was Crucified. O my Soule that thou couldſt bee alwaies me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating upon this Crucifying of Chriſt: Not, that it could be any pleaſure to thinke of his being Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, but the better to make thee apprehend; Firſt the great cauſes of it, thy own ſinne, and his love: and then the great effect of it, thy Everlaſting Redemption: for which thou canſt never bee enough grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if thou bee never ſo little un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mindefull.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dead.]</hi> And now having Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, that Chriſt was Crucified; our next Beliefe is, that hee was <hi>Dead:</hi> and yet how can we Beleeve, that hee could Dye? For, is not Death the Wages of Sinne: and could hee receive the Wages, that had not done the Service? Had
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170922:46"/>committed no ſinne? But is it not, that hee dyed not for any ſinne he committed himſelfe, but for the ſinnes of others which he tooke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him? Even as a Surety payes the Penaltie of a Debt that was none of his owne. And this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> gives, where hee ſaith, <hi>Meſsiah ſhall bee ſlaine, not for himſelfe, but for his people: to make reconciliation for their Iniquities, and to bring in Everlaſting Salvation.</hi> And here appeares ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, why Chriſt <hi>ſuffered under Pontius Pilate:</hi> For the ſame Prophet <hi>Daniel</hi> fore-ſheweth, <hi>That after ſeven weekes, and threeſcore and two weekes, from the going forth of the Commandem at to reſtore and build Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſalem; Meſsiah ſhall bee ſlaine:</hi> Which being computed according to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prophets ſenſe, agreeth juſt with the time, that <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170922:47"/>was Governour in <hi>Judea.</hi> And thus as in the Article before, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was juſtly mentioned, to ſhew that Chriſt was the true Meſſiah, by the circumſtance of his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: So in this Article, <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> is juſtly mentioned, to ſhew that Chriſt is the true Meſſiah, by the circumſtance of the time.</p>
            <p>And for whoſe ſinne was it then, that Chriſt dyed? O my Soule, this Queſtion reflects upon thee; for amongſt others, even for thine: Thy ſinnes were the cauſe that Chriſt was Crucified; Thy ſinnes the cauſe that Chriſt Dyed; and Alas, will be the cauſe to make him Dye continually, if continued: that if there bee any ſparke of Grace, if any life of the Spirit at all in thee, thou wilt now at laſt dye to thoſe ſinnes, that made him to Dye: and every nayle that faſtned him
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170922:47"/>to his Croſſe, will bee a nayle to peirce thy heart.</p>
            <p>But if wee Beleeve that Chriſt was Dead; will wee fix our Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe upon a Dead man? Can we hope for Life from him, who was Dead himſelfe? Indeed, therefore we hope for life from him, becauſe he was dead himſelfe: For if hee had not Dyed, we could not have Lived; ſeeing hee therefore Dyed, that hee might Redeeme us from Death; as it is ſaid of him: <hi>Thou waſt ſlaine, and haſt redeemed us to God by thy bloud.</hi> For, though hee were now dead; yet hee continued not dead long; but after three dayes, wee ſhall heare of his riſing to life againe; and then wee ſhall heare him ſay: <hi>I am hee that liveth, and was dead; and behold, I am alive for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But howſoever, now dead he is,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170922:48"/>and with him is dead all our joy, and all our comfort; but where is the Lamentation that is made for his death? <hi>David,</hi> when he heard <hi>Abſolon</hi> was dead; cryed out, <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Abſolon my Sonne! would to God, I had dyed for thee, my ſonne Abſolon:</hi> but where is any now he heares Chriſt is dead, that crieth out: O deare Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, would to God I had dyed for thee, moſt deare Jeſus? And is it not a grievous thing, that <hi>David</hi> ſhould more lament the death of a wicked Sonne, then we ſhould la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the death of the Sonne of God; and by whom we are made the Sonnes of God? Is it not a ſhame, that a Heathen ſhould ſay of a Heathen, <hi>In ignem poſita eſt, fletur:</hi> and that we hearing <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be dead, ſhould not affoord him ſo much as a teare? Alas, it were well, if we would floore him but
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170922:48"/>the common office of Humanity, to ſee him <hi>[Buried:]</hi> but where are they ſhould doe it? His friends have all forſaken him: Not an Apoſtle now that will be ſeen about him; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf that had made ſuch Proteſtations, what great matters he would doe for his ſake, is ſlunke away and gone; perhaps, to looke after the Sheepe committed to his charge: never regarding what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came of the Shepherd; and if it had not beene for one good man, the bleſſed <hi>Joſeph of Arimathea:</hi> God knowes what Indignities they might have offered to his Sacred Body being dead, who had ſo vile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abuſed it being alive. But thou bleſſed <hi>Joſeph,</hi> hadſt the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſſe to begge his Body of <hi>Pilate,</hi> Tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> tookeſt it downe from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>reſſe, Thou w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ap'dſt it Linnen Cloathes, and laid'ſt it in a Sepulchre, where
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170922:49"/>never man was laid, that as his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die at firſt came out of a Virgins Wombe: ſo now at laſt, it is laid in a Virgine Tombe; thereby per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in myſterie, to honour Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, both in Life and Death. And thou bleſſed <hi>Joſeph,</hi> for this thy pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fact, ſhalt live in the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of men, as long as there ſhall be memories in men; and thy name ſhall bee had in everlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance.</p>
            <p>It may be thought no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, what becomes of the Body, when the Soule is out of it; For lay it where you will, or lay it how you will, it turnes to Duſt: and yet, I know not how, there ſeemes to be a kind of Honour in being fairely Buried: and perhaps, beſides the Honour, a further my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery in it, in what place the Body is laid: For why elſe ſhould <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170922:49"/>be ſo earneſt, to have his Bones carried out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and be brought to <hi>Canaan,</hi> to be buried there.</p>
            <p>But what needes expreſſing in our Creed, that hee was <hi>Buried:</hi> ſeeing what needes beleeving that he was Buried? Our ſalvation had ſufficiently beene wrought by his death, though he had not been buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at all: and is it not then ſufficient, that I Beleeve he was Dead, unleſſe I beleeve alſo that hee was Buried? But ſeeing our ſalvation was wrought by his Death; It was fit to make the Opinion of his death undoubted; and to leave no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the minde about it; which could not well bee done, but by adding, that he was <hi>Buried:</hi> For if he had not beene <hi>Buried,</hi> it might bee thought, hee was but in a Traunce; and then no great matter to revive againe: and ſo his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170922:50"/>have been ſleighted; but Buriall is a thing that conſummates death, and makes men dead, though they were not dead before: as it is reported of the ſubtile Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man <hi>Scotus,</hi> that falling into a Trance, by ſome Fit of Infirmity, he was, whether out of Officious, or Malitious haſtineſſe, ſuddenly buried; and found afterwards, by evident Signes, that he was buried alive. And therefore, to leave no ſcruple for doubting of the true Death of Chriſt, it was neceſſary to be added, that he was <hi>Buried.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now that wee have ſeene Chriſt Dead and Buried: One would thinke, there were an end of Articles of Beliefe concerning him; and yet there are other be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>de, that muſt bee Beleeved no leſſe then thefe: and happy it is for us, that there are other behind:
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170922:50"/>for Alas, if our Beliefe ſhould end in his Death and Buriall, what hope could we have of benefit by belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in him? But now Chriſts hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature conſiſting of a Body and a Soule: and they being by death parted, as that Article tels, what being dead became of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; <hi>[That it was Buried:]</hi> So this next Article tels what became of his Soule: <hi>[That it Deſcended into Hell.]</hi> For his Soule is all the He now, that in this Article is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.</p>
            <p>But is this an Article to make us be glad off? had we not beene better, to have left him at his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead, and lying quietly in his Grave, then to bring him after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to <hi>Deſcend into Hell?</hi> Not at all: For marke the conſequence of this Article; that if notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Buriall, wee ſhould bee
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170922:51"/>doubtfull ſtill of the death of Chriſt; (For one may bee buried for dead, and yet revive againe as <hi>Scotus</hi> did:) Yet this Article that now comes in, will ſtricke the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dead: and indeed, if there were nothing elſe in the Article, but that it makes us infallibly certaine of his Death; It were cauſe enough for giving it a place in this our <hi>Creede,</hi> ſeeing there is nothing that requires ſo great a confirmation, as the death of Chriſt: becauſe upon his death it is, that the maine work of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation depends: and certainely a greater confirmation of his death, there cannot bee then this; that while his Body was lying in the Grave, his Soule deſcended into Hell. For to have the Body in one place, and the Soule in another, both at once, is manifeſtly and infallibly to bee dead: Seeing Death is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170922:51"/>elſe, but to have the ſoule and body to be divided.</p>
            <p>But now concerning his deſcent into Hell; It is wonderfull, what diverſity of opinions there is at this day about it; Partly, concerning the place, and partly, concerning the motion. Firſt, what is meant by <hi>Hell,</hi> and then what is meant by <hi>Deſcending;</hi> ſo differing all in the underſtanding of the words, as if they were not all of one language; at leaſt, had a taint of <hi>Babell</hi> remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtil in them. Some have thought that by <hi>deſcending into Hell;</hi> is meant nothing but the extreame ſorrowes, and torments of ſoule, which Chriſt ſuffered in the <hi>Garden,</hi> and on the <hi>Croſſe;</hi> but this, the time, and order of the Articles, which hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been preciſely obſerved, will not allow; For hee <hi>deſcended</hi> not into <hi>Hell,</hi> till after he was <hi>dead</hi> and
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:170922:52"/>
               <hi>buried.</hi> And beſides, if this were ſo; it ſhould rather bee ſaid, that <hi>Hell</hi> aſcended up to him, then that he <hi>deſcended into Hell;</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, ſeeing thoſe agonies were vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; this <hi>deſcending,</hi> voluntary; thoſe were ſufferings, this an acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Some againe have thought, that by <hi>Hell,</hi> is meant the <hi>Grave;</hi> and by <hi>deſcending into Hell,</hi> his being held under the power of death; but this, the ſoule will not allow: for, the <hi>grave</hi> is a place but for the body, no place for the ſoule; and the ſoule muſt have a place to bee in, aſwell as the body; and it is the ſoule onely, that in this Article is intended. Some others have thought, that by <hi>deſcending into Hell,</hi> is meant the going of his ſoule to the place of all juſt ſoules after death, which is to Paradiſe: but this, the manner of the motion, will
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170922:52"/>not allow; for to Paradiſe cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly is an aſcent, and not a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent; and therefore moſt unlike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that aſcending into Paradiſe, ſhould bee expreſt by deſcending into Hell.</p>
            <p>For though the Poet <hi>Virgil</hi> maks
<q>
                  <l>—amaena vireta</l>
                  <l>Fortunatorum Nemorum, ſedes<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> beatas.</l>
               </q> to be a part of Hell, yet this is but a Poeticall fixion, and not worthy to have place in Divinity: which makes it more plaine; Chriſt told <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> at his riſing, that he was not yet aſcended to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. But to go about to meet with Errour in every corner, would bee both troubleſome and tedious, and perhaps, not worth the labour: It may be ſufficient for us, to ſee the truth by it ſelfe; and <hi>Rectum est Index ſui &amp; Obliqui;</hi> by viewing
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:170922:53"/>the <hi>right,</hi> wee ſhall the better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the <hi>falſehood.</hi> The truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hen in this Article ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes to bee this: That the ſoule of Chriſt being p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rted from his body <hi>deſcended</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally into <hi>Hell,</hi> properly ſo called; though it may ſeeme ſtrange, that having promiſed the good Thiefe, to be this day with him in Paradiſe, he ſhould be this day with the bad Thiefe in Hell; and yet not ſtrange, ſeeing the ſoule is no ſuch ſlow mover, but that it might bee in Hell and Paradiſe, both in one day; and leſſe ſtrange if it bee true, that he meant it, perhaps, of his Deity, and not of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>And that the ſoule of Chriſt did locally <hi>deſcend into Hell</hi> may thus appeare; The ſoule, though a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, muſt yet have a place after its kind to be in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if not <hi>Circumſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> at leaſt <hi>Definitive;</hi> and the ſoule
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170922:53"/>of Chriſt ſtayed not with his body, for then his body ſhould not have been dead; no it aſcended not up to heaven; for, this is a contrary motion to <hi>deſcending;</hi> nor it ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered not about in the ayre, for, this is but a Ficti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of Poets, when they ſpeake of ſoules departed; and what place then remained but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hell? And if it were not the true Hell, into which his ſoule <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended,</hi> then muſt the ſpeech bee Metap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oricall and Figurative; and is a Figurative ſpeech fit to make the Article of a Creede? What though to ſit at the right hand of God, be a Figurative ſpeech, and in the Creed; Is it not a Figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſpeech, which cuſtome hath made Litterall? And is <hi>deſcending into Hell,</hi> a ſpeech made literall by any cuſtome? And if any man be doubtfull ſtill, whether this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170922:54"/>ought to be expounded literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or no: he may doe well to aske counſell of the Article which ſaith; <hi>He aſcended into Heaven:</hi> For, both the Articles being expreſt in a like phraſe, there ſeemes great reaſon to take them both in a like ſenſe; and ſeeing his <hi>Aſcending into Heaven</hi> is certainly meant literally: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore certainely alſo meant literal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his <hi>Deſcending into Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what Authorities have wee for this Interpretation? Indeed, Authorities moſt irrefragable. Firſt, a generall conſent of all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers; Then, of all the learned Writers in the Ages fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: Then in our owne time, of an infinite number wee may name theſe; <hi>Alexander Gyll, John Mayer, Alexander Nowell,</hi> the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Deane of <hi>Pauls,</hi> and chiefely, the learned Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170922:54"/>Thomas Bilſon:</hi> and which is more then all theſe, and not ſlightly to be accounted of, in the directing of our opinions, <hi>The Tenet of our Church of England,</hi> as Deane <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well</hi> writeth in his Catechiſme.</p>
            <p>And as there hath been, and ſtill is, great diverſity of Opinions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his <hi>deſcending</hi> it ſelfe; ſo there hath been, and ſtill is, as great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of opinions about the cauſe of his <hi>deſcending.</hi> But though his <hi>deſcending into Hell</hi> be an Article of our Creed, yet the cauſe for which he <hi>deſcended</hi> is none: and therefore though we be tyed of neceſſity to beleeve that; yet we are at our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty for beleeving of this, and need to beleeve no more of it, then we ſee good reaſon to make it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. And why then ſhould wee trouble our ſelves with debating of circumſtances, which doe but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170922:55"/>ſerve to breed debate? Can wee not beleeve that Chriſt <hi>deſcended into Hell:</hi> unleſſe wee know the cauſe why he <hi>Deſcended?</hi> Should the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> have done well, to forbeare the obeying of Gods Commandement, for wearing cloathes mixt of linnen and wollen: untill they might know the cauſe, why they ſhould not weare them? and doth any man know the true cauſe of it to this day?</p>
            <p>Some indeed, and of the higheſt ranke, hold this opinion; that the cauſe of Chriſts <hi>deſcending into Hell,</hi> was onely to <hi>triumph;</hi> but are there not other, and thoſe no meane ones neither, that are of opinion; he <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended</hi> as wel to <hi>ſuffer</hi> as to <hi>triumph?</hi> Firſt, to ſuffer to perfect our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and then to triumph, to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh our ſecurity? Firſt, to ſuffer, if not the paines of hell, at leaſt,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170922:55"/>ſome paines in hell; thereby to pay the uttermoſt farthing that was due by us: and then to triumph, to receive the firſt earneſt of reward that was due to himſelfe? If his <hi>deſcending into Hell</hi> (ſay they) were onely to ſubdue Satan, and to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over him; why is it ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>David</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt, as a favour of God unto him; <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in Hell.</hi> For what favour was it not to leave his ſoule there, where it was in triumph? It had beene certainly more favour to leave it there, then to take it from thence. It ſeemes therefore, there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which he ſuffered in Hell; in which it was a favour of God, not to leave him; and might have been as miſchieuous to his ſoule, as cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption to his body, if God ſhould have left him in it. They adde, if
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170922:56"/>Chriſt had <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> and had not ſuffered ſome paines in Hell; he had left undone his moſt merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious worke, and had given over meriting, before it came to perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For to be in Hell, and not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair of Gods mercy: to ſuffer paines in hell, and perhaps of hell, and not murmure at Gods juſtice; are works which in making perfection of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſhew perfection of grace; and as without Divine aſſiſtance, they could not be ſuffered: ſo without ſuffering, they could not be done. They adde farther, it is true, he was not thruſt into Hell, as the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned are; who if they were not thruſt into it, would never come there: but he <hi>deſcended</hi> into it, and <hi>deſcending</hi> is a voluntary action, he might have choſen: but as he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſubmitted himſelfe to the death of the Croſſe, in his bodie;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170922:56"/>ſo he willingly ſubmitted himſelfe, to the <hi>deſcent into Hell,</hi> in his ſoule. For, till his ſoule <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> it came not to the loweſt degree of humiliation: and till it came to the loweſt degree of humiliation; it could not come to the higheſt of perfection; and to the higheſt of perfection, it was to come; before he could come to aſcend on high, and to lead Captivity captive. And theſe ſeeme to bee their reaſons, who are of opinion, that Chriſt <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> aſwell to <hi>ſuffer,</hi> as to <hi>triumph.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But may not theſe reaſons bee eaſily made appeare, to bee unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable? For when <hi>David</hi> makes Chriſt to ſay; <hi>Thou wilt not leave my ſoule in Hell;</hi> was it becauſe he ſuffered in Hell; or was it not rather, that though hee onely tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed in Hell; yet his joy of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170922:57"/>triumphing was not ſo great, to make him forget, by whoſe aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance hee triumphed; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to acknowledge, that if God ſhould leave him in Hell; he ſhould haue cauſe to leave triumphing. And to ſay, that if he had not ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Hell, he had left undone, his moſt meritorious worke; Is it not directly to croſſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>That Chriſt pacified all things by the blood of his croſſe;</hi> by which it appeares, that Chriſt ſuffered as much as was neceſſary for our ſalvation upon the Croſſe; and what need then of any more ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, by <hi>deſcending into Hell?</hi> And for degrees of humiliation; doe we reade of any lower: can wee thinke of any lower then this; that <hi>Exinanivit ſeipſum,</hi> he emptied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe of all glory; became of no reputation, and humbled himſelfe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170922:57"/>to the ſhamefull death of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Croſſe? But beſides theſe anſwers, wee may not omit, to obſerve heere a diſtinction which offers it ſelfe, in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles concerning Chriſt, and may ſeeme to give ſome light to the clearing of this Controverſie. For the five firſt Articles ſeeme to concerne Chriſt, as onely a pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: <hi>(Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt: Borne of the Virgin Mary: Suffered under Pontius Pilate: was Crucified, Dead, and Buried:)</hi> all Articles, concerning him as a patient; And in which he did nothing, but onely ſuffered: But the five later Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles concerne him onely as an agent: <hi>(He deſcended into Hell; Hee roſe the third day from the Dead; Hee aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Heaven; He ſitteth at the right hand of his Father; Hee ſhall come from thence, to judge the quicke and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170922:58"/>the Dead:)</hi> all Articles concerning him, as an agent; and as in thoſe of his ſuffering, there is a plenitude of merit: ſo in theſe of his action, there is a plenitude of reward. And now if wee keepe us well to this diſtinction, it will keepe us right in the true underſtanding of this Article: For if hee <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> as an Agent, then not as a Patient; and if not as a Patient, then not to Suffer, but onely to Triumph. Laſtly, if Chriſt <hi>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Hell</hi> to ſuffer, why did not then his body deſcend aſwell as his ſoule; ſeeing our bodies aſwell as our ſoules ſhould have ſuffered the paines of Hell? Which cannot be objected, if wee hold hee <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> but only to Triumph: For as it was a ſufficient and proper tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph for the ſoule to triumph over Hell; ſo it was a ſufficient and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170922:58"/>Triumph for the body, to tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph over death; which it did by riſing the third day, as it followes in the next Article. Indeed, for his <hi>deſcending into Hell,</hi> to triumph over Satan, there was great reaſon; ſeeing hee it was, that had offered him ſo many great indignities here on earth: He it was, that had tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted him in the Wilderneſſe: Hee it was, that put it into <hi>Judas</hi> heart, to betrary him. It was therefore very expedient, that the firſt thing he ſhould doe, when hee came to be an Agent, ſhould be to goe into Hell, to be revenged upon him as it were in hot bloud; and for his greater diſgrace, to triumph over him, within his owne Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now which of theſe opinions is the more probable, perhaps wee may; but which is the truer, who can bee ſure? Seing probability
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170922:59"/>and truth doe not alwaies goe to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; and ſometimes the more true, is the leſſe probable; there being fallacies, aſwell in Reaſon as in Senſe: and indeed, in matters ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and not recalled in Scripture; we may ſooner miſtake all, then take any at all right; and never know in any of them, when we be right, or wrong: and therefore of ſuch poynts, though it may be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated to make Diſquiſitions; yet it is not ſafe to make concluſions. <hi>Sapere ad ſobrietatem,</hi> is an excellent rule in all caſes; but where the truth is but conjecturall, (as in this caſe) moſt of all; and it was juſtly ſaid of Chriſt: <hi>Yee erre not knowing the Scriptures:</hi> For if our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge be grounded, and not upon Scriptures; not onely Errour is eaſily let in, but it is hardly kept out. What the Scripture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170922:59"/>in plaine termes, we may be bold to build upon: but inferences and deductions, are for the moſt part fallacious; ſeldome ſo cleare, to induce a beliefe; ſeldome ſo certaine to breed a knowledge: and therefore in this poynt, our ſafeſt courſe is, to content our ſelves with that which our Creed delivers, that Chriſt deſcended into hell: and not be too curious in examining, much leſſe too peremptory in concluding, either the manner or the cauſes of his <hi>deſcending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if Chriſt deſcended locally into Hell; How could he ever come from thence againe? Seeing it is ſaid, and truly ſaid, <hi>Omnia te advorſum ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantia, nulla retrorſum:</hi> That from Hel there is no returning. No return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeede for thoſe that are dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and are brought thither to live and die there; but for him,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170922:60"/>who <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> to overcome Hell; for him who by <hi>deſcending in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell,</hi> merited <hi>aſcending into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven:</hi> It was not onely poſſible that he ſhould returne, but impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible he ſhould be there detained.</p>
            <p>There have beene Hereticks of old, at leaſt, if they were Hereticks: (called <hi>Pſychopanichitae</hi>) who held this opinion, that when the body dyes, then the ſoule falls aſleepe, and that there is an <hi>Interſtitium</hi> of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as wel in the ſoule, as in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; the ſoule lying aſleep, and not waking till the body at the laſt day riſe againe: becauſe it hath beene ſaid of men when they dyed, <hi>that they ſlept with their Fathers:</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> alſo expreſſeth death by ſleeping: where he ſaith, <hi>For this cauſe, many of you are weake, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſleepe:</hi> and by this meanes, it may bee juſtly ſaid, that when a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170922:60"/>mandies, he knowes his judgement preſently: For though there bee a million of yeares, betweene his death and the day of Judgement; yet the ſoule lying all the while aſleep, they are to him as contiguous And this ſeemes to bee no impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable opinion, and by which many difficult places in Scripture may be cleared; for if it were not thus, how could it be ſaid, that <hi>where the tree falleth, there it lyeth:</hi> for if the ſoule be in action, while the body is dead; how will the Tree lye, where it falleth? Seeing the good ſoules will alwaies be doing of good, and the evill ſoules of evill. But if not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe reaſons, this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion bee not ſuffered to paſſe: Can it better bee confuted, then by that which is ſaid here, <hi>(Hee deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Hell:)</hi> for, what Hee but his ſoule? If then his ſoule <hi>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:170922:61"/>and <hi>deſcending</hi> bee a voluntary action: and no voluntary action but of that which is awake; then certainely, was Chriſts ſoule awake after death, and not aſleep; and if his ſoule, then ours aſwell; ſeeing there is no difference, that we know off, betweene his ſoule and ours, but propenſion to ſinne.</p>
            <p>But what a kind of perſwading is this? to ſeeke to perſwade us to beleeve in Chriſt, by hearing hee was ſcourged and crucified, and hanged amongſt common Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors; and after all this to <hi>deſcend into Hell?</hi> Is he like to be a Saviour to us, that could not ſave himſelfe? For if he had ſaved himſelfe, and come downe from the Croſſe, the Jewes (pretended at leaſt) they would have beleeved in him. But when he did not this, upon ſo juſt a Motive; what reaſon had they
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170922:61"/>but to thinke he could not doe it: and then what reaſon had they to thinke him a Saviour? This indeed was the miſt, that blinded the Jewes eyes: they could never be brought to think him the true Chriſt, becauſe he came in ſuch meanneſſe &amp; humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity: where they looked for a Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias that ſhould come in ſtate; one that ſhould domineere in the world, and reſtore the temporall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the Hebrew Nation. And yet is this one of the maine rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which makes us know and beleeve him to be the true Chriſt; becauſe it is moſt agreeable to all the ancient Prophecies, that ſuch a one the true Chriſt ſhould bee. And indeed ſeeing hee came into the world to bee a Redeemer; and Redeeming conſiſted no leſſe in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering then in doing: It was neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary hee ſhould come in ſuch an
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170922:62"/>Eſtate, as might be fitteſt for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, ſo to pay for us the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt farthing of our debt; not onely by Active, but aſwell alſo by Paſſive obedience, which hee could not have done; at leaſt, not made appeare to have done, if hee had come in ſuch ſtate as the Jewes expected.</p>
            <p>But though he <hi>deſcended into Hell,</hi> and no doubt,
<note place="margin">The third day hee roſe againe.</note> did great matters at his being there; yet it ſeemes he was not long about it; for the <hi>Third day he roſe againe;</hi> Not ſooner then the <hi>third day,</hi> that it might appeare, hee had beene cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly dead: Nor later, that he might not leave his Diſciples too long in diſcomfort: Not ſooner then the <hi>third day,</hi> that there might be time ſufficient for his ſoules triumphing; Nor latter, that there might not be
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170922:62"/>time ſufficient for his bodies cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting: Not ſooner, then the <hi>third day,</hi> that hee might not aboliſh the old Sabbath upon the old Sabbath; Nor later, that he might not leave the world without a Sabbath; for if hee had not riſen till the fourth day, then had the <hi>third day,</hi> beene neither Sabbath-day, nor working-day; Not a Sabbath, becauſe hee was not then riſen, whoſe onely riſing made the new Sabbath; not a working-day, becauſe but one day by it ſelfe, and none of the ſix, that were at firſt ordained to bee working-dayes.</p>
            <p>And now is performed the thing ſignified, of which, <hi>Jonas</hi> was the ſigne; for as <hi>Jonas</hi> went down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Whales belly, and after three dayes was caſt out ſafe upon the ſhoare: So Chriſt having deſcended into the Whales belly, of Hell, was
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170922:63"/>the <hi>third day</hi> ſet a ſhore on the <hi>earth,</hi> and <hi>roſe from the dead.</hi> Now is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified the ſaying of Chriſt, at which the Jewes tooke ſuch ſcandall; <hi>Deſtroy yee the Temple, and in three dayes I will build it up againe:</hi> For when the Jewes had deſtroyed the ſacred Temple of his Body, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him to death upon the Croſſe, in three dayes he built it up againe, and roſe from the dead. And now was verified the Prophecie, <hi>That the glory of the ſecond Temple ſhould bee greater then that of the former:</hi> For ſo was Chriſts body being riſen from the dead; farre more glorious, then the body in which he dyed.</p>
            <p>And now the <hi>third day</hi> being come, <hi>hee roſe from the dead;</hi> but why from the dead? For onely his body from the dead; his ſoule from Hell: and why then from the dead, rather then from Hell?
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170922:63"/>Is not the riſing of his ſoule as wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of our beliefe, as the riſing of his body? And why then, not as well mentioned, as the riſing of his body? But is it not, that to ſay, <hi>he roſe from the dead,</hi> includes them both; ſeeing his body could not riſe without his ſoule: beſides, it more concernes us to ſay, <hi>hee roſe from the dead,</hi> then to riſe from <hi>hell;</hi> becauſe to riſe from the dead, is our owne caſe; but to riſe from Hell, is never like to be the caſe of any, but onely of himſelfe. Neither indeed, can it properly be ſaid, <hi>He roſe from Hell,</hi> ſeeing there can bee no <hi>riſing,</hi> where there was not a <hi>falling</hi> firſt; but though his ſoule <hi>deſcended into Hell;</hi> yet it fell not in Hell, as his body did by death; and therefore proper onely to ſay, <hi>Hee roſe from the Dead, and not from Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Never Cordiall was more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170922:64"/>to a fainting ſpirit; then this Article is to us: The Article before, put us almoſt cleane out of heart: For if his being <hi>dead and buried,</hi> touched us ſo very neerely; how could his <hi>deſcending into Hell,</hi> but touch us to the very quick? But now, this Article of his <hi>riſing from the dead,</hi> puts new life into us; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by this, we are aſſured, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the greatneſſe of his power, that could ſo eaſily vanquiſh <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell:</hi> but of the greatneſſe of his love, that as hee did it for our ſakes: ſo for our comfort, he would come againe, to let us know it. And indeed, though Chriſt did well enough himſelfe, with his <hi>deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into Hell;</hi> yet we for our parts could never well brooke this Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, for two unpleaſing words that are in it; <hi>Hell</hi> and <hi>Deſcending,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamely diſtaſtfull, both. For <hi>Hell</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170922:64"/>is a terrour; and <hi>Deſcending,</hi> a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace: but now, this Article of his <hi>Riſing,</hi> cheeres us up againe; for <hi>Hell</hi> is no terrour, to him that can vanquiſh it; and <hi>Deſcending,</hi> is no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to him that can riſe againe, and indeed, there is nothing that more pleaſeth us then <hi>riſing.</hi> For, as long as we be <hi>riſing,</hi> wee can never doe amiſſe: as the word never gives of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; ſo the action never takes hurt: and ſpecially, if wee riſe, as Chriſt did from the <hi>dead.</hi> For how much the place from which wee riſe, is more hatefull; ſo much the <hi>riſing</hi> it ſelfe is more gratefull; and ſeeing nothing is more hatefull, then <hi>death:</hi> therefore, nothing is more gratefull, then <hi>riſing from the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though Chriſt continued longer dead, then his Diſciples could have wiſhed; yet hee roſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170922:65"/>ſooner from the Dead; then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps they expected: and perhaps they expected not he ſhould riſe at all: For, if <hi>Mary Magdalene</hi> had beleeved that <hi>Chriſt ſhould riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine,</hi> would ſhee have come to the Sepulchre with Spices to Embalme him?</p>
            <p>But how is it true, that Chriſt did riſe the <hi>third day,</hi> when it appeares he roſe before it was day? For the Sunne was not riſen, when Chriſt roſe; and it is the riſing of the Sunne, that makes it day. But though the Sunne were not riſen, yet it was upon riſing, and that was enough to denominate it day. And beſides, before the Sun riſeth, there is alwaies a <hi>Diluculum,</hi> a <hi>day-breake;</hi> and that certainely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to make it bee called, <hi>Day.</hi> But it ſeems, it is meant in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to expreſſe, not only that it was
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170922:65"/>the <hi>third day;</hi> but what time of the <hi>third day</hi> it was, when Chriſt aroſe. And indeed, whether wee take the day, after the account of the Jewes, who begin their day at Sun ſetting; or after the account of the Romans, who begin their day at Midnight, as we do; in both the accounts, it was the <hi>third day,</hi> and then the Sun riſing was the time of the day, in which he roſe.</p>
            <p>But why then would <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalene</hi> come no ſooner with her Spices; ſeeing by this account, the Sabbath day that had hindred her, was ended long before? Was it not, that if ſhee had gone ſooner, ſhee muſt have gone by darke: and could ſhee in the darke, have done the worke ſhee went about? And to have gone by candle-light, would have bred ſuſpition. The Watchmen then might juſtly have
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170922:66"/>ſaid, <hi>His Diſciples came by night, and ſtole him away:</hi> but now ſhee tooke advantage of the firſt light, to bee <hi>going to the Sepulchre;</hi> as Chriſt may be thought at the ſame time, to bee <hi>riſing from the Sepulchre:</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, it was but the diſtance of place, that made the difference of time, betweene her <hi>comming,</hi> and his <hi>riſing;</hi> and it was well, there was that difference of time; For, if ſhee had come ſooner, ſhee had found Chriſt lying dead in his <hi>grave</hi> ſtill; and to have Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balmed him then with her Spices, might have brought imputation upon his <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> have made it be thought, that the vertue of her Spices had revived him; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to prevent this ſcandall, Chriſt was up before <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> came: and as ſoone as the <hi>third day</hi> affoorded but any dawning of
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170922:66"/>light; (for where Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>While it was yet darke,</hi> is but a phraſe of expreſſing, <hi>It was not broad day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light;) He roſe from the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is there not in this a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery? May we not ſay, that Chriſt would not riſe, but with the riſing of the Sunne, becauſe the Sunne could not riſe, but with the riſing of Chriſt. For, as when Chriſt left his life, the Sunne left his light, and was covered with darkeneſſe: ſo now, that Chriſt riſeth from the Dead; the Sunne riſeth from the darke, and makes <hi>the day ſpring from on high</hi> againe with his light. Was it ever heard before, that two Suns did riſe, both together? And why was it ſo now, but to ſhew, that <hi>he is the true light, that lighteth every one that commeth into the world: and that in his light, we ſhall ſee light.</hi> O bleſſed Sunne of Righteouſneſſe,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170922:67"/>as thou didſt then riſe and appeare to thy Apoſtles, with beames of comfort, to remove from them all darknes of ſorrow; ſo vouchſafe now to riſe in my heart, with beames of <hi>grace,</hi> to diſpell from mee all clouds of <hi>errour;</hi> that I may not take thee for a <hi>Cardiner,</hi> as <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> did; but that calling me by my name; I may anſwer thee with <hi>Rabboni,</hi> as <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> did; who though ſhee came too late, to annoint thee with her Spices, <hi>dead:</hi> yet ſhe came time enough, to be the firſt meſſenger of thy <hi>riſing from the dead;</hi> and to have the honour to bee <hi>Apoſtola Apoſtolis,</hi> the Apoſtle to thy Apoſtles; who, but for her inceſſant diligence, might have lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed longer in the ignorance of thy riſing.</p>
            <p>But is it true indeed, that Chriſt did riſe from the dead, and that it
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170922:67"/>is not a tricke put upon us? Seeing he appeared not to all the people, but onely to ſome few men, and are a few men ſufficient witneſſes, to make ſo incredible a thing to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited? But though he appeared not to all the people, yet he appeared to all the Apoſtles, that their holineſſe might well ſupply their number; and to all the Apoſtles at diverſe times, that the frequencie might well cleare them from miſtaking: and if incredulity, notwithſtanding all this, will ſtill bee excepting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their witneſſe; have we not then, more then five hundred bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at once, that ſaw him being riſen from the dead; that if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it not now, having ſo many witneſſes, and ſuch witneſſes to confirme it; neither would wee beleeve it though an Angel ſhould come and tell it us, from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170922:68"/>and indeede, an Angell did come from heaven, and tell it to <hi>Mary Magdalen; He is riſen, he is not here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why would not Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riſen from the <hi>dead;</hi> ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be ſeene of the Jewes: was he affraid, they would Crucifie him againe, as they had done before? but there needed bee no ſuch feare, ſeeing his body was now impaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and not ſubject any more to ſuch indignities. But indeede to what ende ſhould the Jewes have ſeene him? For, it would but have moved them to more blaſphemy; they would but have ſaid, as they had ſaid before, <hi>that he was a Magcian, and had a devill;</hi> and though they had beeue allowed the favour of Saint <hi>Thomas, to put their hands into his ſides:</hi> yet they would never have beleeved him to bee the ſame man,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:170922:68"/>whom they had put to death; but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome Devil that appeared in his likeneſſe: And were theſe fit men to have the favour to ſee Chriſt? The penitent <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> could not be allowed to touch him: and ſhould ſuch reprobate Jewes be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to doe it? even to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples themſelves, he appeared but at times, and in ſhort fits; rather to confirme their beliefe of his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; then to keep them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with his converſation. So as there was cauſe enough why he was not ſeene of the Jewes; but why, after he was riſen, he ſtayed forty daies upon the earth, before he Aſcended; and in thoſe forty daies, appeared nine times, and but nine times to his Diſciples. This indeed is a Myſtery; whereof, without divine Revelation, wee ſhall never come to underſtand the reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170922:69"/>
            <p>But though Chriſts body might riſe from the dead, yet how could it come forth of the Sepulchre; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great ſtone was rowled againſt it, to keep him in? Was it, that the Angel came from heaven, of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pole to let him out? In this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, the Doctors of the Church are much divided; ſome of them holding that the Angel came direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that purpoſe; as amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Authors, Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> (I thinke) the ſecond: and of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter amongſt us, Maſter <hi>Perkins.</hi> Some againe holding, that the Angel row<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led away the ſtone indeed, but not to any ſuch purpoſe, as amongſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; of the Ancients, Saint <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome;</hi> and of the latter, Biſhop <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drewes,</hi> who in his ſeventeenth Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sermon, ſaith thus: <hi>The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel indeed rowled away the ſtone, but Chriſt was riſen firſt: and the ſtone
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170922:69"/>rowled away after.</hi> But ſeeing <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> asked not this queſtion, why ſhould we? Was it not more, that Chriſts body ſhould riſe at all; then that riſing, it ſhould make its way through any obſtacle? And why more, to come out of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre, while the ſtone lay there: then to come in, amongſt his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, when the doores were ſhut? For indeed, who knowes, or is able to define: what the abilities and priviledges of a glorified body are?</p>
            <p>But how are we ſure, that it was the true body of Chriſt that appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; and not rather a phantaſme or ghoſt; ſeeing a phantaſme ſeems alſo to be a body: as the <hi>Samuel,</hi> which the Witch of <hi>Endor</hi> raiſed up to <hi>Saul?</hi> Indeed for this, we are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to Saint <hi>Thomas;</hi> for, his doubting, hath made this out of doubt: For, <hi>putting his hand into his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170922:70"/>ſide,</hi> without which he would not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, hee found it to bee fleſh and bone, of which, a phantaſme or ghoſt hath none; and therefore, though it may deceive the <hi>ſeeing:</hi> yet it cannot deceive the <hi>touching.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here, beſides the litterall ſenſe, there may not unfitly bee drawne a good Morall obſervation: that as Chriſt did not riſe from the dead; till he had firſt deſcended in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Hell; ſo the beſt meanes, to riſe from the death of ſinne, is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend into the Hell and torment of Conſcience, by penitent contrition; and indeed, he that truely feeles the compunction of ſoule for his ſinne; may juſtly be ſaid, to be in hell for the time, ſeeing no hell can mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter greater torment, but yet with this difference: that where in the torment of Hell, there is utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpaire; in this torment of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punction,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170922:70"/>there is aſſured hope. <hi>O gracious God, ſo frame mee to deſcend into this Hell of Compunction, by peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent contrition; that I may never come to feele the torments of that Hell; where there is nothing but weeping and gnaſhing of teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by what power was it, that Chriſt roſe from the dead? For there is great difference betweene <hi>riſing,</hi> and being <hi>rayſed:</hi> to <hi>riſe,</hi> is properly by ones owne power: to be <hi>raiſed,</hi> is properly by the power of another; and they cannot bee both true: and why then are they both ſaid? For as it is ſaid here, that he <hi>roſe;</hi> ſo in another place, it is ſaid, that he was <hi>raiſed.</hi> Is it not that his <hi>riſing</hi> was as his <hi>dying;</hi> vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary and yet impoſed; he <hi>dyed,</hi> becauſe he would <hi>dye:</hi> and he <hi>dyed,</hi> becauſe his Father decreed him to <hi>dye;</hi> and in this, there is no incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170922:71"/>ſeeing all, <hi>Opera ad extra;</hi> all exteriour workes; and all are exteriour works that are not perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall: as they be common to all the perſons in the Deitie, ſo they may be affirmed of the whole Deity.</p>
            <p>After the Article of beliefe,
<note place="margin">He aſcended into Heaven.</note> that Chriſt roſe from the dead: our next Beliefe is, that <hi>he aſcended into Heaven;</hi> and indeed it followes well: For, as when he came downe from <hi>heaven,</hi> he never left deſcending, till hee <hi>deſcended into hell;</hi> ſo now that he is <hi>riſen,</hi> he never leaves <hi>riſing,</hi> till he <hi>aſcend up to Heaven.</hi> And ſo my ſoule, ſhouldſt thou doe, not thinke it enough to riſe up from ſinne, and there ſtay; but never leave riſing, till thou aſcend up to Heaven as Chriſt did.</p>
            <p>But what? <hi>Aſcend</hi> as ſoone as he was <hi>riſen?</hi> What time was there
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170922:71"/>then, for <hi>Thomas</hi> to put his hand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ſide? What time for <hi>Peter</hi> to take charge of his Sheepe? Hee therefore <hi>aſcended</hi> not preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his up-riſing; but ſtayed forty dayes upon earth before he <hi>aſcended;</hi> in which time, hee appeared nine times to his Apoſtles and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. But what needed he to have ſtayed fortie dayes, if hee appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but nine times? Or why ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared hee but nine times, if hee ſtayed fortie dayes? Indeed, to give the reaſon of the number of his times of appearing; and why at other times hee concealed himſelfe: is perhaps a ſecret be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond our capacitie: Onely in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, wee may conceive, that hee appeared ſometimes, to make his Diſciples aſſured of his <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection;</hi> and he forbore appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſometimes, to weane them
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170922:72"/>from their carnall deſire of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. He appeared ſometimes, to inſtruct them in many things which they knew not before; and he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore appearing ſometimes, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare their mindes for his <hi>aſcending.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But howſoever, by theſe his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearings, hee manifeſted foure fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of a <hi>glorified body;</hi> that it can vaniſh away at pleaſure; that it can eate or faſt at pleaſure; that it can alter ſhape at pleaſure; that it can enter, where the doores are ſhut: For all theſe Chriſt did after his <hi>riſing,</hi> by vertue of his <hi>glorified body:</hi> But that his <hi>Body,</hi> though <hi>glorified,</hi> was at any time in more places then one at once, is no where to be found in the holy Scriptures, and can never bee proved by the Word of God.</p>
            <p>But to what Heaven was it that <hi>Chriſt aſcended?</hi> Not as ſome foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170922:72"/>interpret thoſe words of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid; In Sole poſuit tabernaculum ſuum,</hi> as though hee placed his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle in the Sunne, and went no higher: For, if this were ſo, how could he come to ſit at the <hi>right hand of his Father,</hi> whoſe throne is in the higheſt heavens.</p>
            <p>This <hi>aſcending of Chriſt into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> makes juſtly a high Feſtivall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, which wee call <hi>Aſcenſion day;</hi> but ſhould we not rather call it <hi>Aſcenſion yeare,</hi> or ſome longer time then a <hi>yeare;</hi> at leaſt, if wee meane it as long as the time hee ſpent in <hi>aſcending.</hi> For if it were leſſe then yeares, it may be written for a Wonder: ſeeing <hi>Alpharabius,</hi> a great Aſtrologer amongſt the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabians,</hi> affirmes for certaine, the <hi>Starry-Heaven</hi> to be ſo high above the Earth, that a man with reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble journeyes, could hardly goe it
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170922:73"/>in eight thouſand yeares: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Aſtronomers affirme, the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Earth to the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermoſt Heaven, to bee no leſſe then foureſcore Millions of miles: And another expreſſeth the diſtance thus, that if a Mill-ſtone were fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling downe from Heaven, it would be neere a hundred yeares in falling, before it came to the Earth. And if wee wonder at theſe things (as indeed they are moſt wonderfull) wee may conſider what juſt cauſe there is, to have this Attribute gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to God, to be the <hi>Maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth.</hi> But though the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of place be ſo great, and the motion of a naturall body bee ſo ſlow; yet what is this to a glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed body, that makes no reckoning of diſtance of place; but <hi>inſtar ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guris,</hi> like Lightning, is able to move from any part of the world
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170922:73"/>to another in an inſtant; that if we meaſure the length of the <hi>Feſtivall,</hi> by the length of the time which Chriſt ſpent in <hi>Aſcending;</hi> we need not call it <hi>Aſcenſion day,</hi> but <hi>Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion minute:</hi> ſeeing his <hi>glorified body</hi> was able in a minute, to paſſe from the Earth to the higheſt Heavens. And though, when hee began his <hi>Aſcent from Mount Olivet,</hi> hee ſet out at firſt ſo ſlowly, that if he went no faſter, he was not like to get to Heaven in many yeares: yet that was done, but <hi>ad paſcendos Diſcipulorum oculos;</hi> as it were to feed his Diſciples eyes: to the end, they might the better obſerve his <hi>Aſcending,</hi> and be the more ſenſible of it; and perhaps, to ſhew how unwilling hee was to leave them. For afterward, no doubt, hee men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his pace, and made uſe of the agility of his <hi>glorified Body;</hi> and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170922:74"/>perhaps, was arrived in Heaven, while the Angel ſtood blaming the Apoſtles, for gazing up after him.</p>
            <p>But if he had been <hi>Aſcended into Heaven</hi> ſooner, why did he not ſend the Holy Ghoſt downe upon his Apoſtles; till after fifty daies, that he began his <hi>Aſcending:</hi> that ſo hee might have kept his promiſe: <hi>And loe, I am with you alwayes to the ende of the world:</hi> meaning, either by himſelfe, or by the Holy Ghoſt: where now there were fifty dayes; in which, they neither had Chriſt, nor the Holy Ghoſt amongſt them? <hi>O my ſoule, what preſumption is this: to inquire into Myſteries that are hidden from us, and will be ſtill, till wee come our ſelves to heaven, from whence the Holy Ghoſt was ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ground have wee for it, that Chriſt indeed <hi>aſcended into Heaven?</hi> Seeing Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> and
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170922:74"/>Saint <hi>John,</hi> who were likely to have ſeene it, ſpeake nothing at all of it; onely Saint <hi>Marke</hi> and Saint <hi>Luke,</hi> who ſaw it not, and had it but at the ſecond hand; record it to us; and is it reaſon, to beleeve them that ſpeake but by heare-ſay; when eye witneſſes, if any ſuch thing were, are ſilent; eſpecially, in a matter of ſo great conſequence as his <hi>Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> is? It is true indeed, Saint <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew,</hi> for what cauſe I know not, breaks off his Goſpel before Chriſts <hi>Aſcending;</hi> but Saint <hi>John,</hi> though hee ſpeake not of it, in the place, where the other doe; yet hee had delivered it, at leaſt, intimated it, before in his Goſpel, where hee mentions Chriſt to ſay, <hi>What, and if yee ſhall ſee the Sonne of man aſcend up, where he was before?</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> a Witneſſe without exception, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes plainely, <hi>That more then five
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170922:75"/>hundred brethren at once ſaw him Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending;</hi> and himſelfe alſo, though he ſaw him not <hi>Aſcend,</hi> yet he ſaw him being <hi>Aſcended:</hi> that nothing can have a more ſure ground of Beleeving: nothing bee more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, then Chriſts <hi>Aſcending</hi> into Heaven.</p>
            <p>And of his <hi>Aſcention,</hi> wee may eaſily conceive, two ſpeciall ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects: One, which we are ſure off; the other, which wee hope: the firſt, his owne glory; that having received indignities on earth, hee might receive the reward of them in Heaven: the other, our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort; <hi>that where he is, we may be alſo.</hi> O bleſſed Saviour, I know not whether more to grieve, for thy <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending into Hell;</hi> or more to joy, for thy <hi>Aſcending up to Heaven:</hi> yet I muſt confeſſe, there is advantage on the joyes part: For, though one of
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170922:75"/>them was to thee moſt prejudiciall: yet both of them are to mee moſt beneficiall.</p>
            <p>There are many that aſcend: (for we are all of a climbing nature) but not into Heaven: They aſcend but with <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> up into the Ayre; the popular ayre of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and glory of the World: and alas, they preſently fall downe againe, becauſe the thin Ayre is not able to beare them up; and <hi>the end of theſe men is worſe then the beginning.</hi> There is no Aſcending good, but into Heaven: For, once come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there will be no falling down againe; For though <hi>Lucifer</hi> did ſo once; yet it is never like, to bee done ſo any more.</p>
            <p>It was never heard, that any <hi>Aſcended up to Heaven</hi> till now, but onely <hi>Elias</hi> the Prophet: a type perhaps of Chriſts <hi>Aſcending,</hi> who
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170922:76"/>aſcended up in a <hi>fiery Chariot;</hi> and wee may marvell, how hee could ever get to Heaven, and not bee burnt by the way; but indeed, the fire of his Chariot, was perhaps, the ardour and burning love of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphins:</hi> which like the fire that appeared in the Buſh to <hi>Moſes, though it burnes, it never conſumes.</hi> And thou my ſoule, if with this ardour and burning love of God, thou couldſt enflame thy heart; thou alſo might'ſt Aſcend up to Heaven in a <hi>fiery Chariot,</hi> as <hi>Elias</hi> did.</p>
            <p>But though <hi>Elias</hi> went up into Heaven; yet it cannot properly be ſaid; that he <hi>Aſcended into heaven:</hi> For he was taken up in a <hi>Fiery Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot,</hi> and to bee taken up, is by the power of another; to <hi>Aſcend,</hi> is by his owne power; and this, <hi>Elias</hi> did not, nor ever any, but onely Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="141" facs="tcp:170922:76"/>
            <p>But though Chriſt <hi>aſcended into Heaven;</hi> yet he <hi>aſcended</hi> not as the ſoules of the Saints doe:
<note place="margin">He fitteth at the right hand of God.</note> to lye under the Altar, when they come there: but he Aſcended, <hi>to ſit at the right hand of God the Father Almighty:</hi> For, who indeed, is fit to ſit at the right hand of the Father, but his onely Sonne? And now, by his <hi>Aſcending,</hi> a great alteration is made, in the order of taking place in Heaven. For where before, the Cherubins, or Seraphins; or what other Order, is the higheſt, in the Hierarchy of Angels, tooke their places next to God. Now the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature of Chriſt, takes place before them all: that if <hi>Lucifer</hi> were now in Heaven, he might have juſter cauſe, to murmur at Gods par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality, as he would call it, then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he bad, when he firſt revolted.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:170922:77"/>
            <p>But we muſt not here bee ledde with the weake conceit of fleſh, or with the vaine conceit of errour; as though God were a body, and had a right hand and a left hand, like to us; who is <hi>purus Spiritus,</hi> a pure and ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Spirit; but as we make account, that to fit at our right hand, is to have the higheſt place, next our ſelves, ſo when Chriſt is ſaid to ſit at the Right hand of his Father; it is meant, that all power is given him both in Heaven and Earth; at leaſt, a power far ſupreme then any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; a ſoveraigne power over all creatures. And this, my ſoule, makes well for thee, and for us all; for we may bee ſure, hee ſits not there for his owne glory onely, but as well alſo for the good of his Church; that by ſitting there, he may bee the readier to make conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall Interceſſion for us: for alas
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170922:77"/>if it were not by this benefit, how were it poſſible, his <hi>little Flocke</hi> ſhould have been able to withſtand ſo many Aſſaults, as have moſt vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olently beene made upon it in all Ages.</p>
            <p>O Bleſſed Jeſus; thou well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedſt to ſit at the right hand of the Father, who didſt offer up thy ſelfe, a perfect ſacrifice of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to thy Father; Thou well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveſt to have the higheſt place in Heaven, who didſt humble, thy ſelfe to the loweſt place in Hell: Thou art worthy to have all knees bow to thee both in Heaven and Earth; who didſt drinke the bitter Cup of thy Fathers wrath; to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile all things unto him, both in Earth and Heaven. And though in the time of thy Pilgrimage upon Earth, thou wert faine to flee out of <hi>Judea</hi> into <hi>Egypt;</hi> and faine to ſtand
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170922:78"/>as a Priſoner at the Barre of <hi>Pilate,</hi> and faine to hang nailed on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed Tree; and faine after all, to lie buried in a Grave: (all Poſtures of miſery) yet now at laſt, thou art come to a Poſture of reſt; For <hi>thou ſitteſt:</hi> and to a ſeat of glory; For <hi>thou ſitteſt at the right hand of thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> and there ſhalt ſit in reſt and glory, till the time come, that thou come to give juſt ſentence upon them, who gave unjuſt ſentence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thee, and to bee avenged of all thine enemies. For as we beleeve that <hi>Chriſt ſitteth at the right hand of his Father;</hi> So we beleeve <hi>hee ſhall come from thence, to judge both the quicke and the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how can wee beleeve that <hi>Chriſt ſhall come to judge the quicke and the dead,</hi>
               <note place="margin">From thence he ſhall come to judge, &amp;c.</note> when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelfe that hee <hi>Judgeth no
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:170922:78"/>man.</hi> It is true indeed, he judged no man while he was here upon earth, to be judged himſelfe: but now that all power is given him both in heaven and earth; wee beleeve, it is a part of that power; <hi>that he ſhall come to jduge both the quicke and the dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when will the time of his comming bee? O my ſoule, thou maiſt well reſt ſatisfied, with that anſwer of Chriſt to his Apoſtles; <hi>It is not for you to know the times and ſeaſons, which God hath lockt up in his owne breaſt.</hi> Yet ſee the vaine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitiveneſſe of mans nature, that would know that, which is hidden from the Angels; and more then this, from the Sonne of man him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; although it may ſeem ſtrange, that he ſhould not know the day of Judgement: who is himſelfe, to be the Judge? and yet not ſtrange,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:170922:79"/>ſeeing to appoint the day of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, belongs to him that appoints the Judge; and is perhaps one of the things, which makes God ſay; <hi>Secretum meum mihi,</hi> My ſecret to my ſelfe: but moſt of all, my ſoule, it may be enough for thee, that thou art ſure to heare newes of thy own judgement ſoone enough; even as ſoone as thou leaveſt this ſinnefull body: and as for the generall Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, thou needeſt not trouble thy ſelfe, when, or how long, it ſhall be a comming: ſeeing, though it may perhaps encreaſe thy particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar judgement, yet it ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it.</p>
            <p>And as wee are uncertaine of the time; ſo wee are no leſſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine of the place: For though we beleeve from whence he ſhall come; yet wee have no beliefe, whither he ſhall come. It hath bene
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170922:79"/>a received opinion by ſome, that he ſhall come into the Valley of <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi> and keepe his Seſſions there: but alas, what is the Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of <hi>Jehoſophat,</hi> to receive the innumerable number of perſons, that muſt make their appearance there; ſcarſe the whole earth, would be roome enough to make a Seſſions-houſe for ſuch a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: unleſſe perhaps, by the like miracle, as is ſaid to have beene u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuall in the Jewiſh Synagogue; that when the people kneeled downe, there was roome enough in the Temple to hold them all; but when they ſtood up, they were fain, many of them to goe out of the Temple, for want of roome; when yet kneeling downe muſt needs take up more roome, then ſtanding up.</p>
            <p>But though we know not, either at what time, or to what place hee
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170922:80"/>ſhall come; yet we beleeve to what purpoſe hee ſhall come; For; <hi>hee ſhall come to judge the quicke and the dead: The quick,</hi> thoſe whom hee ſhall finde alive at his comming; and <hi>the dead,</hi> thoſe who dyed before his comming: Or <hi>the quicke,</hi> thoſe that are alive in grace: and <hi>the dead,</hi> them that are dead in ſin. But not to judge the dead, while they are dead; for ſo, they ſhould not bee able to anſwer for themſelves; which cannot ſtand with the juſtice of ſo righteous a Judge; but at his comming, at the ſound of a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet; <hi>The Sea and the Earth ſhall give up their dead, and they ſhall all ariſe, and ſtand at his Tribunall, to receive their ſentence, of pardon or condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, according to their works.</hi> And oh! how terrible will that day be? For if the day were terrible in which the Law was given; ſo terrible,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170922:80"/>that <hi>Mount Sinai</hi> was all of a ſmoake; how terrible will that day bee, in which the tranſgreſſors of the Law, ſhall all be brought to receiue their Triall? If the day were terrible which was a day of grace; how terrible will the day be, which ſhall be a day of puniſhment? O my ſoule, let the remembrance of this Article be never out of thy minde; and if at any time thou find in thy ſelfe, either ſuggeſtions of Satan, or motions to ſinne; then thinke upon this Article; and when thou thinkeſt upon it, beleeve it; and be moſt aſſured, that there ſhall moſt certainly bee a day of judgement; in which all thoughts of the heart, though never brought forth in words, ſhall bee diſcovered; all actions of life, though never ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly done, ſhall all be laid open; and judgement ſhall be given upon
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170922:81"/>them all, without favour, or parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alitie. And let us not flatter our ſelves in ſecurity, becauſe he who is now our Advocate, ſhall be then our Judge; but rather conſider, that though hee be now a Lambe, he will then be found to be a Lyon; <hi>Demonſtravit potentiam, qui demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtravit patientiam;</hi> and let us pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare our ſelves againſt that day in feare and trembling; and let us ſend up ſtrong cries to him; that as the good Thiefe, obtained to be remembred of him, when he came into his kingdome: ſo wee may obtaine of him, to be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred in mercy, when he comes to judgement.</p>
            <p>Before wee leave this Article; there is one obſervation which may not be omitted; that this Article is of a different making from all the reſt: all the other might bee
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:170922:81"/>made by Apoſtles; but this ſeemes rather to bee made by a Prophet: For our beliefe in it is Propheticall, and tells what Chriſt will doe in time to come. Indeed, none of the Articles concerning Chriſt; are in the Future tenſe but onely this; as none of them is in the Preſent tenſe, but onely the next before, <hi>He fitteth at the right hand of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> all the other Articles are in the Preter perfect tenſe, and ſpeake of the time paſt: even from his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, to his <hi>aſcending into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> in the Preterperfect tenſe, all: but once <hi>aſcended into Heaven,</hi> where all time is Preſent; no more Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terperfect tenſe then, no more men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of time paſt, and therefore our Article turnes Preſent too, <hi>He ſitteth at the right hand of his Father;</hi> and there ſhould ſit and enjoy his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent tenſe, and time for ever, if
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170922:82"/>it were not for us: but as once before, for our ſakes hee left Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and came downe to redeeme us: ſo once againe, for our ſakes hee will leave Heaven, and come downe to judge us. For without judging, he could not come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding. No comming to <hi>Venite benedicti Patris, Come yee bleſſed of my Father;</hi> untill hee have judged firſt: and without comming to this <hi>Venite,</hi> all that went before, would come to nothing. And therefore all the benefit of theſe Preterper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect tenſes, conſiſts in this Future; all the harveſt I may ſay, of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Articles, is reaped in this laſt; that <hi>Chriſt ſhall come to judge the quick and the dead;</hi> O therefore my ſoule, be carefull to lead thy life ſo in this preſent world, that thou maiſt not bee afraid of his comming to judgement; becauſe of <hi>Ite maledicti
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170922:82"/>in ignem aeternum, Goe yee curſed into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting fire;</hi> but maiſt rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce at his comming, becauſe of <hi>Venite benedicti Patris, Come yee bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of my Father:</hi> For, as that <hi>Ite,</hi> will pay them home for all the pleaſures of a wicked life; So this <hi>Venite,</hi> will make amends for all the preſſures of a wretched life: and indeed without the benefit of this <hi>Venite,</hi> all the delights and pleaſures, the world can afford; will prove but as <hi>Naboths</hi> Vineyard to <hi>Ahab,</hi> Coroſives in the end.</p>
            <p>And now having beleeved in the firſt and ſecond Perſon of the Trinity,
<note place="margin">I beleeve in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</note> the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son:</hi> if wee ſhould not beleeve in the third Perſon, the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> wee ſhould doe him great wrong, and our ſelves more: ſeeing it hath been through him, and by his aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170922:83"/>that we have beleeved in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For, as it is true, that the <hi>Holy Ghoſt proceeds from the Father and the Son:</hi> ſo it is true, that beleeving in the <hi>Father &amp; the Son, proceeds from the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> For beleeving being a work of <hi>Faith;</hi> and Faith a worke of Sanctification, and Sanctification a worke of one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> how ſhould wee come to beleeving, but by the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt?</hi> And it is indeed for this, that he hath his Name to be called the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> or <hi>Spirit.</hi> Not but that the Father and the Sonne, are both Holy and Spirits, as well as he; but becauſe it is properly <hi>Hee,</hi> that inſpires our mindes with all good thoughts, and holy deſires. And now, my ſoule, while I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in the <hi>Father,</hi> as the author of my Creation; and in the <hi>Sonne,</hi> as the author of my Redemption; and in the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as the author
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170922:83"/>of my Regeneration; that all the Perſons in the Deity, may have their ſeverall operations in me, and beſtow their ſeverall gifts upon me; will there not be cauſe of my thankefulneſſe to every one of them; and of returning to every one of them, all praiſe and glory, who are all of them but one.</p>
            <p>But why is there ſo much ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of Chriſt, and ſo little of the Holy Ghoſt; being a Perſon in the Trinity, as well as hee? Is it not, that there is more ſpoken of the Sonne then of the Holy Ghoſt, in regard of the Sonnes being In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnate, and taking our nature up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: For, this indeed, brings in many points to bee beleeved; whereof, conſidered onely as the ſecond perſon in the Trinity, there ſhould be no need. So as the two Natures in Chriſt muſt needs give
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170922:84"/>cauſe to have more ſpoken of him, then of the holy Ghoſt, that hath but one nature.</p>
            <p>The Doctrine concerning the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> hath in all Ages beene moſt obſcure; ſo much, that in ſome Churches it was ſome time before it was beleeved at all; or ſo much as knowne, <hi>whether there were a Holy Ghoſt, or no:</hi> even in theſe preſent times, the <hi>Greeke</hi> Church, a Church of great extent, differs thus from us; that where we beleeve the Holy Ghoſt, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from the Father and the Son; that Church beleeves the Holy Ghoſt to proceed from the Father by the Sonne; a nice difference in ſo Incomprehenſible a Myſtery, that there ſeemes no juſt cauſe to lay ſuch <hi>Anathemaes,</hi> as ſome doe: upon that Church for ſo beleeving.</p>
            <p>If wee ſhould beleeve in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170922:84"/>and in the Sonne, and not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in the Holy Ghoſt, this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe would never be ſanctified, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Ghoſt onely is the Sanctifier; and ſanctifies none, that beleeve not in him: and the beliefe not being ſanctified, would never bee acceptable to the Father him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, notwithſtanding our beliefe in him. And this perhaps, was the cauſe, why the Offering of <hi>Cain</hi> was not accepted: becauſe, though a Sacrifice, yet it wanted a devotion ſanctified by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>There is a ſinne which is proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called, <hi>The ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and for them that commit this ſinne, we are forbidden to pray: a grievous ſinne, no doubt; which ſtops the current of Charity, whoſe nature is wont to overflow al banks: but what the ſinne is, and by what marks it may certainly be known;
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170922:85"/>though a Queſtion much agitated, is not yet ſo fully explicated, but that it leaves ſcruples: but what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever it is, or may be; we may be ſure, that the Not-beleeving in the Holy Ghoſt, is one principall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient in it; Or rather, where a true beleeving in the Holy Ghoſt is, this ſinne properly can never bee committed. And therefore in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king profeſſion of our Faith, there is none of all the Articles in the whole Creed, that ſeemes more neceſſary to be ſaid then this: For by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Article, we make it appeare there can bee no danger in praying for us; as not being likely to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, who beleeve in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But why is it, that ſinnes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Father, or the Sonne, ſhall bee forgiven: but a ſinne committed againſt the Holy
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170922:85"/>Ghoſt, ſhall never bee forgiven; neither in this world, nor in the world to come? Is it not, that if a ſinne bee committed againſt the Father, or the Sonne; the Holy Ghoſt being the Sanctifier, can ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie that ſinne, and make it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable; but if a ſinne bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt the Holy Ghoſt, there is none to ſanctifie it; and not being ſanctified, it juſtly exceeds all bounds of Remiſſion. O therefore thou bleſſed God the Holy Ghoſt: Vouchſafe to endue me with a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of ſanctification, that what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſinnes ſoever I may happily unhappily commit; yet I may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be ſo unhappy to commit this dreadfull ſinne, of ſinning againſt thee.</p>
            <p>When we read the order of the Perſons in the Trinitie; the Father placed firſt; the Sonne, ſecond;
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170922:86"/>the Holy Ghoſt laſt: wee muſt not conceive it, as though there were any Priority betweene them in time; who are all Go-eternall: or any diſparity betweene them in dignitie, who are all Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall; but that it is an expreſſing of Order onely to our capacities; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing although they be Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet they are all but One God: All but One in Subſtance, though Three in Subſiſtence. The Incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibleneſſe of which Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, though it exceed our capacities; yet not our Beliefe; Or therefore the fitter for beliefe, becauſe it ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds our capacities.</p>
            <p>And now having profeſſed our Beliefe, in <hi>God the Father, God the Sonne,</hi> and <hi>God the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> wee may juſtly conclude, and ſay, <hi>O Holy, Bleſſed, and glorious Trinity; Three Perſons, and One God, have
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170922:86"/>mercy upon us miſerable ſinners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus is finiſhed the firſt part of our Creed, <hi>In whom it is we Beleeve:</hi> the other part remaines, containing <hi>What it is we Beleeve:</hi> For to know <hi>In whom to beleeve,</hi> and not know <hi>what to beleeve,</hi> were to ſtand at a gaze, and bee to ſeeke, when wee come to our leſſon. Indeede, the things wee beleeve, have depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon the Perſons in whom we beleeve; and ſuch dependance, as without beleeving in thoſe, wee cannot truely beleeve theſe. If wee did not beleeve in the Holy Ghoſt, we could not beleeve the <hi>Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church,</hi> nor the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> for theſe are benefits, that come by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt;</hi> And if we did not beleeve in the Son of God, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> we could not beleeve the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> nor the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170922:87"/>of the body,</hi> for theſe are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits that accrue unto us, by the Sonne of God Chriſt Jeſus: And if we did not beleeve in <hi>God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> we could not beleeve <hi>the life Everlaſting;</hi> ſeeing by him onely it is, that we live, and have our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent being, and ſhall have our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall being.</p>
            <p>And the firſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of this kinde is this:
<note place="margin">I beleeve the holy Catholike Church.</note> 
               <hi>I beleeve the Holy Catholike Church.</hi> I beleeve it in deed, but not in it, as I doe in God: For this is a Priviledge due onely to him; and beſides, if I ſhould beleeve in it, I ſhould beleeve partly in my ſelfe, as being a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of it: but I beleeve, there is a <hi>Holy Catholike Church. Holy,</hi> as in which are the Elect of God, and <hi>Catholike,</hi> as in which are of all Nations under heaven: and this is
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170922:87"/>not the Church of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> for that Church, though at ſome time, it were <hi>Holy,</hi> yet it was never <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike,</hi> as being bounded within <hi>Canaan:</hi> but now as the Holy Ghoſt hath made the Church <hi>Holy,</hi> by ſanctifying it; ſo Chriſt hath made it <hi>Catholike,</hi> by enlarging it: for at his comming, at leaſt, at his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away, he broke downe the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition wall,</hi> by his laſt Warrant to the Apoſtles: <hi>Goe teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and of the Sonne, and of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though Chriſt ſet his Church at large, yet not long after his time, a Sect of Hereticks would needs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine it againe: For <hi>Donatus</hi> and his followers, would perſwade the world, that as before the true <hi>Church</hi> was onely in <hi>Canaan:</hi> ſo now, the true Church was onely in <hi>Africa:</hi>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:170922:88"/>but by beleeving the <hi>Holy Catholike Church:</hi> I now diſclaime both theſe Churches, the Church of the Jewes, as not being <hi>Catholike,</hi> and the Church of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> as being neither <hi>Catholike</hi> nor <hi>Holy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what uſe is there of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle? May not a Chriſtian man doe well enough, and yet leave this Article out of his Creed? Indeed, there is not onely great uſe of it, but even neceſſitie. For ſeeing there is no ſalvation out of the Catholike Church; what aſſurance could I have of my ſalvation, if I did not beleeve, that there is a <hi>Catholike Church?</hi> How can I beleeve my ſelfe to be a member of that Body, which I doe not beleeve to bee? For this <hi>Holy Catholike Church,</hi> is the number of all thoſe, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God hath <hi>Predeſtinated and Elected:</hi> and though the Catholike Church may have in
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170922:88"/>it errours, and perhaps Hereſies: yet the <hi>Holy Catholike Church</hi> can have none in it, but Orthodoxe and true beleevers. For it is as the Arke of <hi>Noah,</hi> to ſave all that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the comming of the Flood: but unbeleevers are all excluded from entring into it; It is as the Corporation of the Citizens of the <hi>New Hieruſalem,</hi> in which, <hi>whoſe names are not Enrolled:</hi> (and none are <hi>Enrolled, that beleeve not,) they can bee no partakers of the Heavenly Priviled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges;</hi> of which, <hi>Salvation is the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi> If there were not a <hi>Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church;</hi> then <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould be a Shepherd without a Flocke; then <hi>God the Father,</hi> ſhould bee a King without a People; then the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> ſhould bee a guide, and have none to lead: but the Two firſt of theſe, are aſſured us by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>Feare not little Flock, For it
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170922:89"/>is your Fathers pleaſure to give you a kingdome:</hi> and the laſt, where hee ſaith, <hi>Hee will ſend the Holy Spirit to lead them into all truth.</hi> Therefore there is an <hi>Holy Catholike Church;</hi> which, he that beleeves not is not of it; and not being of it, can have no hope of ſalvation by it.</p>
            <p>To be <hi>Holy</hi> and <hi>Catholike,</hi> are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the proper Caracters of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church; the firſt repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof, was then, when at Pentecoſt, there met at <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> of all Nations under heaven: <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyans, and Medes, and Elamites, and the dwellers in Meſopotamia and Judea, in Cappadocia, Pontus, and Aſia, Phry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, and Pamphylia, in Aegypt, and in the parts of Lybia; and ſirangers of Rome, Jewes and Proſelites, Creetes and Arabians:</hi> For here was no boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding within <hi>Canaan,</hi> no bounding within <hi>Africa,</hi> but the Church was
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170922:89"/>made apparent by plurality of Nations, to bee Catholike, and by viſible graces to be Holy.</p>
            <p>This Church therefore, I beleeve to be holy, yet not holy in perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but tending to perfection; and juſtly called holy, for its Inchoati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and I beleeve it to bee Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, but Catholike in doctrine, not in diſcipline; and therefore the rule of it as concerning doctrine is this, <hi>Quod ab omnibus, Quod ubique, Quod ſemper:</hi> For if it be not <hi>ab Omnibus,</hi> It is not Catholike in Perſons: if not <hi>Vbique,</hi> not Catholike in place; if not <hi>Semper,</hi> not Catholike in time; and all theſe muſt concurre, to make the Church be Catholik in Doctrin: In Diſcipline, not ſo; for there, neither <hi>ab omnibus,</hi> nor <hi>ubique,</hi> nor <hi>ſemper</hi> is required: but it may be va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and diverſe, according to the diverſity of Time and Place; and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170922:90"/>yet in doctrine bee the Catholike Church: For Diſcipline is but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Eccleſiaſticall, where Doctrine is divine.</p>
            <p>This Article bindes my beliefe to no particular Church, as it is a particular, but as it is a Member of the Catholike: For take it by it ſelfe, without conſidering it, as a Member of the Catholike Church: and it is not ſo properly a Church, as a Conventicle; which though I cannot deny, but it may be Holy, at leaſt in a Morall holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: yet I can deny, that I am bound to beleeve it to be holy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am bound to beleeve no true holineſſe to bee out of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church.</p>
            <p>This Catholike Church is a Schoole of inſtruction, to teach us as much as we are bound to know, and a Rule of direction, to informe
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170922:90"/>us as much as wee are bound to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve: if it were but onely what Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> ſaith: this might make us doubt of Chriſts reſurrection: or if it were but onely, what Saint <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> ſaith, this might make us incline, to comply with the Jewes: but when it is that, which all the Apoſtles with one conſent ſay, this is the voice of the Catholike Church, and can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make us to goe aſtray. And ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to this Church, I ſubmit all my faculties, both my underſtanding to her decrees; and my will to her counſels; and make account, that if I know any thing, and not of her inſtruction, it will prove but falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood; if doe any thing, and not by her direction, it will prove but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: For, this that Spouſe of Chriſt, of which it is ſaid, <hi>Thou art all faire, and there is no ſpot in thee.</hi> Oh then, let not me beginne to make any ſpot
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170922:91"/>in the face of thy Spouſe, O Lord, but ſo purge me with Hyſope, that though I be not pure, yet I may bee cleane; at leaſt not ſo foule, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file others; nor deſerve with <hi>Miri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> to be put out of the campe of thy Militant Church, but may come to thy Triumphant. As therefore this Article is the firſt of all we have to beleeve, ſo let it have the honor that is due to the firſt, and have the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place in our beliefe; For indeed, all the Articles that follow, are but as flowres that grow in the garden of this Catholike Church: <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints,</hi> as the flowre of Charitie. <hi>The forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> as the flowre of Faith: <hi>The reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the body,</hi> as the flowre of Hope; <hi>and the life everlaſting,</hi> as the flowre of reward: if I may not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, as the whole noſegay of all the other flowres together; ſeeing
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170922:91"/>in this, they have all their ſmels u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited into one fragrant odour; Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity raiſed to perfection, Faith tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into love, and Hope into en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joying.</p>
            <p>But what ſhould be the cauſe, why amongſt theſe Articles that are to be beleeved, there is no mention at all made of the Scriptures? For, ſeeing we are commanded to ſearch the Scriptures; No doubt, it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wee ſhould beleeve the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and if we ſhould beleeve them, why are they left out in the Article of our beliefe? Is it not that theſe were Articles of Beliefe for a Chriſtian man, before any Goſpell of Chriſt was written? and how then could they have any place in the Creed; when they had not as yet any being in the world? For the life and doctrine of Chriſt, was publiſhed by word, before it
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170922:92"/>was recorded by writing; and the Apoſtles preached it, before the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts writ it: and this Creede being a Breviate and ſumme of that which was preached; who can tell but it may bee more antient then that which is written? at leaſt being the ſubſtance of them both: what more is it to beleeve the Scripture, then the Creed? And then what neede is there to have them named, when they are expreſt? And as for the words of Chriſt, <hi>Scrutamini Scripturas,</hi> Search the Scriptures: or, yee ſearch the Scriptures; if we extend them no further, then Chriſt ſpake them, we may be farre enough off from beleeving the Goſpel. For Chriſt ſpake then but of the Olde Teſtament, and not of the New, which at that time was none. For the firſt Goſpell that was written of Chriſt, was that of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:170922:92"/>which was not writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, til eight years after Chriſts death; the other, much later; eſpecially that of Saint <hi>John,</hi> which was not written till thirty yeares after, and therefore the Creede, no doubt, was delivered, if not in forme, as now it is; at leaſt in ſubſtance, as now it is; long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore any Goſpell was written.</p>
            <p>And may it not bee further ſaid, that this Creed ſeemes to have been penned, when Religion was firſt tranſlated from Judaiſme to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie: and therefore that there are no other Articles in it, then ſuch as are in oppoſition to the doctrine of the Jewes; by introducing in their place, the Chriſtian beliefe: For by the Article of beleeving in <hi>God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> we utterly renounce the doctrine of the Jewes, who acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge no Trinity of Perſons in the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170922:93"/>Deity. By beleeving the Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Sonne of God, Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and his paſſion under <hi>Pontius Pilate,</hi> we renounce the doctrine of the Jewes, who teach, that the true Meſſias is not yet come. By be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving the <hi>Holy Catholike Church,</hi> wee renounce the opinion of the Jewes, who thought that the Church of God was bounded onely within <hi>Canaan,</hi> and that no Church could be holy, but that of Iſrael. By be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> we renounce the doctrine of the Jewes, by which, a Jew indeed would take no uſury for money of a Jew; but to any of another Nation, they would uſe oppreſſion, to the very grinding of their faces. By belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Phariſees Juſtification by workes; and ſticke onely to the Publicanes Juſtification by Faith, <hi>O
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170922:93"/>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi> By be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> we renounce the errour of the Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, whom Chriſt confuted by this argument, <hi>Have ye not read that which was ſpoken to you by God, ſaying, I am the God of Abraham, the God of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaak, and the God of Jakob: God is not the God of the dead, but of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> By beleeving the <hi>life everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,</hi> we renounce the opinion of the Jewes, who depended onely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on temporall benefits, and the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of this life; and as for the life to come, were as careleſſe of it, as ignorant. And now, ſeeing all the Articles of this Creed, are in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the doctrin of the Jewes; what marveile, that in it there is no Article for beleeving the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as concerning the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that were then, there was no oppoſition beweene the Chriſtians and them.</p>
            <pb n="176" facs="tcp:170922:94"/>
            <p>It may with more reaſon bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, why in theſe Articles of beliefe; there is no mention made of the Sacraments: ſeeing Baptiſm and the Lords Supper were ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt himſelf, and are things ſo neceſſary to be beleeved? But is it not, that of Baptiſme Chriſt ſaid; <hi>Goe teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the name of the Father, of the Sonne and of the holy Ghoſt:</hi> and of the Euchariſt he ſaid, <hi>Doe this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me;</hi> and ſo both theſe are things of Action, which wee muſt not onely beleeve, but doe; and therefore fitter placed, <hi>Inter agenda,</hi> amongſt the records of things to be done; then <hi>Inter credenda,</hi> amongſt the Articles of things to be belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Catholike Church</hi> is no ſooner founded,
<note place="margin">The Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints.</note> but the <hi>Communion of Saints</hi>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:170922:94"/>followes preſently upon it; as was ſeene at the <hi>Pentecoſt,</hi> after Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſts Aſcending, when the Holy Ghoſt deſcended upon the Apoſtles in clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Tongues; for then were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of all Nations under Heaven, who it ſeemes, made the repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative body of the Catholike Church: and then being all of one accord, and having all things in common and diſtributing to every one as they had need, they acted the Article we here beleeve.</p>
            <p>If there were not a <hi>Communion of</hi> S<hi rend="sup">ts</hi>, the wicked ſhould be more chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table then the godly: for among the wicked there are leagues and confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracies, and they hold together for the common good; and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their lives are engaged for one another: and if the wicked doe this, the godly certainely, will doe it much more; and this makes me to
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170922:95"/>beleeve aſſuredly, <hi>The Communion of Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But are there Saints then on earth? Are not all men living, ſinners? and can ſinners be Saints? Indeed, not Saints by Canonization of men, but by the Canonization of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit: Not Saints in perfection, but in Inchoation; called Saints, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; <hi>becauſe called to be Saints, as having their Names written in the Booke of God in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we muſt here take heed of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> Communion of Saints: For by their Communion, no man ſhould have any thing in private; but all ſhould be in common; and ſo, none ſhould be richer or poorer then another: which would make Chriſts Praediction directly falſe; where hee ſaith, <hi>The poore yee ſhall have alwaies with you:</hi> and would make all theſe exhortations voide:
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170922:95"/>
               <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your Father which is in Heaven. Charge them which are rich in this world, that they be ready to give, and glad to deſtribute. Give Alme, of thy goods, and never turne thy face from any poore man.</hi> But indeed, this Communion is in part expreſt by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> where he ſaith, <hi>Doe good to all men, but eſpecially to thoſe of the houſhold of Faith.</hi> For the being of one houſhold, implies plainely a common proviſion for al the houſe, but implies withall, a diſparity of eſtates.</p>
            <p>Indeede, the firſt flowre that growes in the Garden of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church,</hi> is the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> which as it begins in the Militant, ſo it continues in the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant Church: Continues there when the other flowres are withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170922:96"/>and gone: For when <hi>Faith and Hope ſhall be no more, yet Charity ſhall continue;</hi> and not onely continue, but be then moſt flouriſhing: and if we did not beleeve <hi>the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Saints,</hi> wee could not truely ſay, <hi>Our Father</hi> in the Lords Prayer: for in ſaying <hi>Our Father,</hi> wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe this Communion.</p>
            <p>But for the better underſtanding of this Article; It may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that there are Saints on Earth, and Saints in Heaven; and this Article containes the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of them both; both of the Saints on earth between themſelves, and of the Saints in Earth and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with one another. What though they bee farre diſtant and aſunder? Are not the feet ſo from the head: are not the hands ſo from the heart? Yet if there were not a relation and correſpondencie betweene them:
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170922:96"/>neither the feet would bee able to move, nor the hands to ſtirre, and perhaps not the head in many things to doe his Office.</p>
            <p>And this Communion conſiſts, either in Aſſiſtance, or in Love; but in Aſſiſtance, for a time; in Love, for ever. For as the Saints in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven aſſiſt us, by praying, that wee may ſo leade our lives in this life, that we may come to bee admitted into their Societie in the next: So we aſſiſt the Saints in Heaven, by praying, that the ſuite which they make, lying under the Altar, may be heard and accompliſhed. They pray for us, that we may be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes; and wee pray for them, that they may be partakers of the Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the body. But as this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Aſſiſtance is but for a time; ſo the Communion of Love
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:170922:97"/>will be for ever: For we ſhall love one another, and bee loved of one another, as Members of one Body, as Inhabitants of one Citie, and as Fellow-labourers in the worke of exalting Gods glory; a work, which becauſe it ſhall never end, there ſhall therefore, never be end of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion.</p>
            <p>If the Communion bee of the Saints on earth betweene them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, this is viſible charity; as it is ſaid, <hi>If yee love not your brother, whom yee ſee; how can yee love God, whom yee doe not ſee.</hi> And it conſiſts in ſupplying what wants ſoever we ſee in a brother, as farre as wee are able; and in doing to others, as we would be done unto our ſelves. If the Communion bee of the Saints in Heaven between themſelves, this is Intellectuall Charitie; and it conſiſts in a reciprocall love they
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170922:97"/>beare one to another, in regard of the love they beare all to God. If the Communion be of the Saints in Heaven, towards the Saints on Earth; this is condoling charity, and it conſiſts in a griefe they take at any ſinnes, we commit; leaſt wee ſhould not be found blameleſſe, at the great day of the Lords appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. If the Communion be of the Saints on Earth, towards them in Heaven; this is a congratulating charity, and it conſiſts in a pious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, at the happineſſe wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive they enjoy, in the fruition of God, and of his bleſſed Angels.</p>
            <p>This Communion of Saints, is a <hi>Gazophylacium,</hi> or Treaſurie, where there is receiving indeed, but not without contributing: we muſt do our parts to it, or never looke for any part in it; and it is to be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, there are many Hereticks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170922:98"/>us, concerning this Article, that either underſtand it not; or at leaſt, beleeve it not: For if they did truely beleeve <hi>the Communion of Saints,</hi> were it poſſible, they ſhould paſſe by the man lying wounded in the way, and not doe as much as the <hi>Samaritan</hi> did; take care of his curing? It is, no doubt, good to obſerve the Rule, that <hi>Charitie begins at home:</hi> but it is good alſo to underſtand the Rule; and to know what is meant by <hi>home;</hi> for the <hi>Home of Charitie,</hi> is included in the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends as farre, as the releeving of a needy brother. But alas, becauſe <hi>Charity ſeekes not her owne,</hi> therefore ſhe her ſelfe is not much ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and while Charity is negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted: this Article ſtands in our Creed, but as a Cypher; and as well we may forbeare to fay <hi>we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170922:98"/>it;</hi> as forbeare to ſhew by our actions that <hi>we Beleeve it:</hi> Or rather, better indeed to leave it out of our Profeſſion, then not to take it into our Practiſe. And this Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is therefore neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved, becauſe it is the flowre of <hi>Charitie,</hi> and muſt be ſet in our hearts betimes: that it may take the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per root, as that which ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, when the flowres of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope</hi> ſhall be faded and gone.</p>
            <p>And now having ſpoken of the two Articles,
<note place="margin">The forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes.</note> that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly relate to the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> It followes to ſpeake of the two next Articles, which properly relate to the Sonne of God, <hi>Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> whereof this is the firſt, <hi>I beleeve the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes.</hi> And indeed, after the <hi>Communion of Saints;</hi> this Article followes very fitly, ſeeing
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170922:99"/>there is ſeldome any mention made of <hi>Forgiving of ſinnes;</hi> but that there is mention made of <hi>Charity</hi> alſo; as in the Prayer taught us by Chriſt, we ſay not, <hi>Forgive us our treſpaſſes,</hi> but ſay withall, <hi>as we forgive them that treſpas againſt us:</hi> For, <hi>Love co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the multitude of ſinnes;</hi> and the ſinnes being covered, they are the more eaſily forgiven afterward.</p>
            <p>But whether the connexion of this Article to the former, bee for this reaſon, or no; there are certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this Article many great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: For, if there were not <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> the whole world ſhould bee damned. For, all the World being guilty of ſins, and the <hi>Wages of ſinne being death:</hi> if that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be not forgiven, how ſhall any man be ſaved? But ſeeing there are which are <hi>Elect, and ordained to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> this makes me aſſuredly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170922:99"/>the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we ſhould not beleeve the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſinnes;</hi> Why have wee Beleeved, that Chriſt was Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? For, why was hee Crucified but to pay the penalty of our ſins? And the penalty being paid, how can the ſinnes but bee forgiven? To what end was all the ſuffering of Chriſt, but to ſatisfie his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers juſtice; That laying the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity of his juſtice upon him, hee might conferre the benefit of his mercy upon us; and how is his mercy conferr'd, but by <hi>Forgiving of ſins?</hi> If we ſhould not Beleeve the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe of ſinnes;</hi> how could wee beleeve that God were merciful? ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the chiefeſt act of Mercy, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in <hi>Forgiving?</hi> And to deny God to be mercifull; what were it, but to deny him the moſt glorious, and the moſt eminent of all his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes?
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170922:100"/>ſeeing his mercy is above all his workes. Alas, if we did not beleeve the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes;</hi> in what miſerable affliction ſhould our mindes be? For knowing firſt, that we cannot but commit ſinnes day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and then knowing, how grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly our ſinnes provoke the wrath of God againſt us: and laſtly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, how fearefull a thing it is, to fall into the hands of the living God; in what a miſerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhould we be, if we did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes?</hi> If I ſhould not beleeve the <hi>Forgivenes of ſinnes;</hi> what hope could I have they ſhould ever be <hi>forgiven?</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the meanes I have in my ſelfe, to procure their <hi>forgiving,</hi> is onely my beliefe, that they ſhall be <hi>Forgiven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O how comfortable an Article is this; which makes it be truly ſaid
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170922:100"/>of Chriſt: <hi>In odore vnguentorum tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum curremus poſt te;</hi> In the ſavour of thy ſweet Ointments wee will run after thee. For with this Oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hee healeth all our ſores, he makes us whole in all our diſeaſes; he makes us ſtrong in all our Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. O my ſoule, if at any time, thou either by infirmity, fall; or by allurements, be entiſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſinne; then have recourſe to this Article: <hi>I beleeve the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes,</hi> and thou ſhalt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find in it, both reſt and refreſhing to thy fainting ſpirits.</p>
            <p>And of what ſins is it then, that <hi>I beleeve the forgiveneſſe?</hi> Indeede of all ſinnes, how great or many ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they bee; for ſeeing there are no limits of Gods mercy, neither is there any bound of his <hi>forgiving.</hi> And therefore, though m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinnes be more then the haires of my head,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170922:101"/>though a burden farre greater then I can beare; yet I beleeve the <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe</hi> of them all.</p>
            <p>But if I beleeve the Forgiveneſſe of all ſinnes, doe I not then beleeve the Forgiveneſſe of a ſinne <hi>which ſhall never be forgiven?</hi> For is there not a ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>which ſhall never bee forgiven either in this world, or in the world to come:</hi> and ſo my Beleeving will prove a falſe Beliefe, and deceive mee in the end. It is true indeed, that ſuch a Sinne there is; but is it not that the chiefeſt Ingredient of that ſinne, is the not-beleeving the <hi>Forgivenes of ſinnes?</hi> And therefore hee that truely beleeves this Article, is never likely to commit that ſinne; ſeeing the beleeving being from the Holy Ghoſt, the ſinne againſt the Holy Ghoſt can never be committed.</p>
            <p>But is this the uttermoſt of our
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170922:101"/>beliefe, to Beleeve the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes?</hi> Is there no place for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeving the <hi>Merit of Workes?</hi> If there be, why hath it not here a place in our Creed? Indeede, in the <hi>Phariſees</hi> Creed, it might perhaps have a place: but in the <hi>Penitent Publicanes</hi> Creed, ſuch as wee profeſſe our ſelves to be, what place can it have? ſeeing all his beliefe is terminated in this, <hi>O God be mercifull to me a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</hi> Indeed, as <hi>Solon,</hi> amongſt all his Lawes, made no Law againſt Parricides; not, that hee did not thinke them worthy of Puniſhment; but becauſe he thought, there would never bee any ſo unnaturall, and therefore thought it not needfull to make a Law againſt a <hi>Non futurum,</hi> againſt a fault that was never like to be committed: So in our Creede, there is no Article, of the Merit of good works: Not that good works
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170922:102"/>may not Merit; but becauſe ſuch Meritorious works are never like to be done by any; and therefore not fit to make an Article of a <hi>Non futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> of a thing, though poſſible, yet not likely: or rather, ſo farre from being likely, as not being poſſible. And indeed, which of the Apoſtles can we thinke, ſhould have been the Author of ſuch an Article? Saint <hi>John,</hi> we may be ſure would not; For he ſaith plainely; <hi>If we ſay wee have no ſinne, there is no truth in us;</hi> and where there is ſinne, there can be no Merit. Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> we may be ſure, would not: for, though there was a time, when hee thought hee could doe wonders of good works, and even dye with Chriſt; yet when it cam to the point, he was glad to bewaile his infirmitie with teares: and to ſay to Chriſt, when time was, <hi>Depart from me, for I am a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170922:102"/>man.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> wee may well thinke, would not; For hee profeſſeth directly, <hi>To glory and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in nothing, but in the Croſſe of Chriſt crucified:</hi> And for what ſerves the Croſſe of Chriſt, but for the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes?</hi> And by the judgement of theſe Apoſtles, wee may judge of the reſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no defect of our Creed in this, but the uttermoſt bounds of our Beliefe in this point; beyond which there is no <hi>Plus ultra,</hi> goes no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then this, to Beleeve the <hi>Remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and forgiveneſſe of ſins.</hi> We may indeed labour, &amp; we muſt labour to do good works, the beſt we can; but all the Merit of it, is but this, and it is a great Merit too; that we cannot rightly beleeve the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of our ſinnes;</hi> if wee doe not labour, not to ſinne, and doe our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, to doe good works. O my
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170922:103"/>ſoule, all we have to truſt too, all we have to hold by, is the <hi>Forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes:</hi> For, theſe are they that make God angry with us: and theſe <hi>forgiven,</hi> will reconcile him. Theſe are the cauſes why he turnes away his <hi>bleſſed face from us:</hi> and theſe, <hi>forgiven,</hi> will make his <hi>couu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance to ſhine upon us:</hi> all Merit muſt be aſcribed to him onely, in whom they are <hi>forgiven:</hi> between whoſe Merit, and his Fathers mercy; I know not how to diſtinguiſh; and therefore take them both but as one motive, to make me <hi>Beleeve</hi> the <hi>Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes:</hi> All of us, have onely ſinne, Chriſt onely hath Merit, his Father onely hath <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſſe; For with him there is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and plentious redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But may not a ſinne be <hi>forgiven;</hi> and yet the Penalty be ſtill in arere? Was not the ſinne of <hi>David</hi> with
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170922:103"/>
               <hi>Bathſheba forgiven,</hi> and yet puniſhed afterward by the death of the child, that was begotten of her? It is true indeed, the life of the Child was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away indeed, but this was not properly a puniſhment for the ſinne, but a caſtigation of the ſinner, to make him the better to reſent his ſin, and to bee the more wary after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of committing the like. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, it may be thought rather a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, then a puniſhment to <hi>David;</hi> for in taking away the life of the Childe, there was that taken from him, which upon his repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, would have beene a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all eye-ſore to him, if it had lived; according to that of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul, What fruit have yee of thoſe things, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of yee are now aſhamed?</hi> Withall, it was not perhaps without Myſtery; to ſhew, that the pleaſures of ſinne never beare but blaſted fruits, which
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170922:104"/>fall off the tree, before they come to ripeneſſe.</p>
            <p>But at what time is it, we beleeve that ſinnes may bee forgiven? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed at all times, as long as ſinnes may be committed; which is all the time, that wee are living in this world: but if once we be dead, as there will be then no more commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſinne; ſo neither will there be any more <hi>forgiving</hi> of ſinne: <hi>but where the tree falleth, there it will lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But is there not a ſinne, of which it is ſaid, <hi>It ſhall never bee forgiven, either in this world, or in the world to come?</hi> And why is this ſaid, but becauſe a ſinne may bee forgiven, in the world to come, though it be not forgiven in this world; and this perhaps, is a cauſe, why ſome have conceived, that in the world to come, even the Divels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſhall bee forgiven. But is it
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:170922:104"/>not that the Not-forgiving of ſins in the world to come, is therefore mentioned; becauſe in the world to come, ſhall be pronounced the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Not-forgiving: and ſo it is but as to ſay, it ſhall never be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given in this world, upon private conviction; nor in the world to come, upon publicke condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For otherwiſe, it is moſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, if abſolutely a ſinne bee not <hi>forgiven in this world, neither ſhall it ever bee forgiven in the world to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is no ſmall impediment to the beliefe of this Article, that there are few, who thinke they ſinne at all; but are of the Phariſees mind, and their Conſciences are as cleare as Chryſtall: and of thoſe againe, that thinke they ſinne, there are few that know the greatneſſe of their ſinne; but they judge of their ſin,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170922:105"/>as of the Moone: this little becauſe farre from their ſight; that little, becauſe farre from their thought. And of thoſe againe, that know the greatneſſe of their ſinne, there are few that ſay with <hi>David, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my iniquity, and my ſinne is ever before me.</hi> For ſinne being an unplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſight, they love not to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, more then needs they muſt, &amp; while they looke not upon the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſe, they looke not after the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; and ſo between the little know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſinne, and the little acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging of ſinne: the beliefe of this Article is in no little danger to be very little; only Faith ſtands in the breach: and ſupplies all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and it is the worke of Faith; and indeed of a great Faith, that can truly ſay, <hi>I beleeve the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There have been Hereticks of old,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170922:105"/>who held this opinion; that no fins ſhould be forgiven, that were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted after Baptiſme; and they grounded their opinion upon the ſaying of Saint <hi>Paul; If wee ſinne wilfully after we have received know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the truth, there remaineth no more Sacrifice for ſinnes;</hi> and ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves upon this Text, they would neither Baptiſe others, nor be Baptized themſelves, till in their old age; making account that Age having repulſed in them inordinate deſires; they might ſafely then bee Baptized, without feare of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting any wilfull ſinnes after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. But would any man beleeve, that men of common ſenſe, could ever fall into ſo groſſe an errour; eſpecially, having heard it ſaid, <hi>At what time ſoever a ſinner repenteth him of his ſinnes, I will put all his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe out of my remembrance, ſaith the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170922:106"/>Lord.</hi> That we may ſee, it is not time that prejudiceth Gods <hi>forgiveneſſe;</hi> whether before Baptiſme, or after; whether ſooner, or latter: but come at any time, and bring <hi>Repentance,</hi> and God at no time will be wanting to <hi>Forgiveneſſe.</hi> For as it is mercy in God, which is the motive to us, to <hi>Beleeve the forgiveneſſe of ſinnes;</hi> ſo it is <hi>Repentance</hi> in us, that is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to God, to <hi>Forgive us our ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But why is the <hi>Forgivenes of ſins,</hi> put here <hi>inter Credenda,</hi> amongſt things to be Beleeved; and not ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>inter Agenda,</hi> amongſt things to be done: ſeeing to Remiſſion of ſinnes, there belongs Repentance, a thing to bee done; and without <hi>Repentance,</hi> no <hi>forgiveneſſe.</hi> Is it not that <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> is an effect of <hi>Faith;</hi> and therefore juſtly pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced amongſt things to be Beleeved; and though <hi>Repentance</hi> be neceſſary
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170922:106"/>to come in the <hi>Recre,</hi> yet <hi>Faith</hi> muſt lead the <hi>Vant-gaurd,</hi> and have the Preceedence: For if <hi>Faith</hi> goe not before, <hi>Repentance</hi> will not follow; indeed, cannot follow, ſeeing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Faith, <hi>It is impoſsible to pleaſe God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now my ſoule; obſerve the great extent of this Article, it keeps mee from ſinning againſt the Holy Ghoſt, whilſt <hi>I beleeve the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſinnes,</hi> by his inſpiring; it appeaſeth the wrath of God the Father, whilſt <hi>I beleeve the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> in onely his mercy: It glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies his Sonne Chriſt Jeſus, whilſt I beleeve Gods mercy, through onely his Merits; that ſeeing this Article is reguardant to all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Trinity, I may hope that by beleeving it, all the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the Trinity, will be reguar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant upon me; and ſpecially, the Sonne. For indeed, this Article,
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170922:107"/>and the next that followes, are two flowres I may ſay, that grow up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very Grave of Chriſt. For as there is no <hi>Forgivenes of ſinnes,</hi> but onely by the vertue of his death: ſo there is no <hi>Reſurrection of the body,</hi> but onely by the operation of his <hi>Riſing from the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus farre wee are brought by this flower of Faith: <hi>I beleeve the Forgivenes of ſinnes:</hi> The next is the flower of Hope,
<note place="margin">The Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Body.</note> by which wee <hi>Beleeve the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Body;</hi> and it followes indeed, very fitly; for ſeeing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy dyed not at firſt, but by reaſon of ſinne; what ſhould hinder, if ſinne bee forgiven, but that the bodie ſhould riſe againe, and returne to life? This indeed, is a flower ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hard of growing; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> growne, ſends forth a moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="203" facs="tcp:170922:107"/>ſavour: and as, of all the Articles in the Creed, there is none more hard to be beleeved; ſo once beleeved, there is none that miniſters greater comfort. For, what need I care, though my body bee laid in the grave, and bee turned to duſt; ſo long as I am ſure, and undoubtedly beleeve, that hereafter it ſhall <hi>riſe againe,</hi> and bee in the ſame, but a better ſtate then now it is: In the ſame for ſubſtance, but in a better for quallities and endowments.</p>
            <p>If there were no Reſurrection of the body; then neither the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhould have Reward in their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, nor the wicked, Puniſhed; but ſeeing both the godly ſhall bee Rewarded in their Bodies, and the wicked, Puniſhed; therefore there ſhall bee a Reſurrection of the Body.</p>
            <p>This Article, no doubt is hard to
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170922:108"/>be beleeved; For, who would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, there ſhould be <hi>Regreſſus a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptione ad generationem, a privatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad habitum:</hi> a going backe from Corruption to Generation; from Privation to Habit; a thing impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in Nature, and improbable in Reaſon; yet this impoſſibility in Nature, this improbality in Reaſon muſt be beleeved; before wee can beleeve the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body.</hi> Who would beleeve, that a Body conſumed to duſt, and that duſt ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered by the wind into a thouſand places, ſhould ever be brought to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againe, to be the ſame body it was before? who would believe that a Body devoured, perhaps, by wild beaſts; perhaps, eaten by Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes; and by digeſtion become a part of thoſe Beaſts or Fiſhes; ſhould ever returne to be the Body of a man againe; as it had beene
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170922:108"/>before? Indeed, none would beleeve it, that looked only upon the power of Nature, as were ledde only with the light of Reaſon; but when we looke upon a Power that is ſtronger then Nature, and are led by a Light that is brighter then Reaſon: what ſhould hinder, why we ſhould not beleeve it? Shall we not beleeve the <hi>Reſurrection of the body,</hi> becauſe we know not by what wayes it ſhall bee rayſed? Is it not enough, that we know the power of Gods wayes; but that we muſt alſo know the waies of his Power? Doe we know, how the body at firſt is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Mothers wombe; and would we looke to know, how it ſhall bee formed the ſecond time, in the wombe of the Earth? Have wee profeſſed by the firſt Article of our Creed, that God is <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> and will we not allow him to do
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170922:109"/>the works of an Almighty? Doe we beleeve that nothing is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for God to doe, and yet thinke, there is this thing, which he cannot doe? Looke upon the Corne, when it is caſt into the earth; and after a few daies, you ſhall ſee it to bee nothing but as a kind of corruption; and yet of that corruption, doth God make the ſame Corne to ſpring up againe; and to bee as flouriſhing, as it had beene before: and if God doe this in the Corne, ſhall hee not as well doe it in our bodies?</p>
            <p>But, it is not perhaps, that wee doubt of his Power, but of his Will; ſeeing his Will is not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to doe all hee can. And can we doubt of his Will; his Will ſo often revealed to us in his Word: ſo firmely aſſured to us by his Word; <hi>This is the Fathers Will,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:170922:109"/>which hath ſent me; that of all which he hath given mee, I ſhould looſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; but ſhould raiſe it up againe at the laſt day.</hi> And in another place, <hi>This is the Will of him that ſent mee; that every one that ſeeth the Sonne, and beleeveth on him, may have everlaſting life; and I will raiſe him up at the laſt day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now if we be ſatisfied of his Will; ſhall we fall back againe into a relapſe of doubting his Power? But alas, is it any hard matter, for God to make the ſame body again, which hee had made once before? Or is it harder for him, to make a Body the ſame it was before; then it was to make it at firſt, when it was not at all? Is it not eaſier for God, to make a Body out of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; then it was at firſt, to make it out of nothing? Is it any hard mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for God, to reduce all Bodies to
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:170922:110"/>their firſt Elements; and then to mixe and compound them againe, as he did at firſt? When our Bodies were firſt made, they were made but of duſt; and when they are dead, they ſhall but be turned into duſt; and cannot God take the ſame duſt, to make the ſame body againe, as well now, as hee did then? What though it bee ſcattered about in a thouſand places: is diſtance of place any thing to God, who is equally in all places at once? Is it hard for God to know, which is the proper duſt of every particular Body, and to give to every one their own duſt; whoſe knowledge extends to count the juſt number of the ſand, and to call all the ſtars of Heaven by their names? Is there any duſt upon the Earth, any mote in the Sun, which God hath not made? And if hee have made them all by his power,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:170922:110"/>ſhall he not diſpoſe of them all at his pleaſure? If by onely ſaying, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregentur Aquae:</hi> God made the great Ocean, which we cannot look upon without wonder; Can he not as well, by onely ſaying, <hi>Congrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Pulvis,</hi> make the duſt of all Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies come together again; that every Body may be the very ſame Bodie, it was before? Say a Body be devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Beaſts; be eaten of Fiſhes: ſo as by digeſtion, it become a part of their Bodies, ſay it ſuffer never ſo many alterations; yet all thoſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations ſhall be reſolved at laſt, into the ſame duſt it was at firſt: and cannot God of the ſame duſt, make the ſame Body againe; as well now as he did before? God of nothing made the duſt of the Earth; and of that duſt, the Body of man; and though the duſt which was made of nothing, ſhall returne againe to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:170922:111"/>yet the Body of man, that was made of duſt, ſhall never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to leſſe then duſt; and to ſo little, ſhould never have returned neither, if God for mans tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion had not denounced againſt him, <hi>Pulvis es &amp; in pulverem reverteris:</hi> If then Gods ſaying, <hi>Duſt thou art, and to duſt thou ſhalt returne;</hi> have been the cauſe of the Bodies retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to duſt: why ſhall not his ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>A Body thou art, and a Body thou ſhalt riſe againe;</hi> be as well a cauſe of the <hi>Reſurrection of the body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, if we be ſatisfied of his power; ſhall wee fall back againe into a relapſe of doubting his Will? But why did God make the Body of man of duſt; where he made the bodies of Beaſts of nothing; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, the bodies of Beaſts, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe to nothing: where the Body of man ſhall never returne but
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:170922:111"/>into duſt, that out of that duſt; it may riſe againe, to be the ſame Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy it was before? Why did God make the Body of man himſelfe; where he commanded the Earth to bring forth the Bodies of other Creatures; but becauſe he meant it a further preſervation, then hee meant other creatures; and what further preſervation, if the body did not riſe againe?</p>
            <p>And if now againe we bee ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of his Will; ſhall wee fall backe into another relapſe of doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his power? Cannot God doe as much upon a ſudden, as Nature can doe with Time? Though Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture muſt have nine Moneths lying in the Mothers wombe, before it can make a mans Body perfit; yet God made <hi>Adam</hi> a perfect Body in an Inſtant; and could he tranſcend Nature then, and can he not now?
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:170922:112"/>Is he growne to bee as impotent as Nature: able to doe no more, then what naturally may be done? What though the world doubt it, and <hi>Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducees</hi> deny it; ſhall we rather aſſent to them, then ſay with <hi>Job, Though wormes deſtroy this Body, yet I ſhall ſee God in my Fleſh:</hi> And if ſee God in his Fleſh, then muſt his Body riſe againe, that hee may have Eyes to ſee him.</p>
            <p>And as theſe be ſome reaſons of many, to ſhew, that the <hi>Reſurrection of the body;</hi> may be. So there are other reaſons as ſtrong, to ſhew that it ſhall and muſt be. When <hi>Moſes</hi> met <hi>Chriſt</hi> on the Mount; how came hee by his Body againe, which had beene dead and buried many hundred yeares before? How came thoſe men by their bodies againe, who having beene dead and buried, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſe at the time of Chriſts riſing;
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:170922:112"/>and appeared unto many in the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Citie? When Chriſt at the laſt day ſhall ſay, <hi>Venite Benedicti Patris, Come yee Bleſſed of my Father;</hi> hee ſhal not ſay it to the ſoule alone, nor to the body alone, but to the whole man; and if to the whole man, then muſt the body bee joyned to the ſoule againe, that it may be a whole man; but no ſuch conjunction, if no <hi>Reſurrection of the Body.</hi> Is not Chriſt our head, and we his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and if hee Aſcended up to Heaven in body and ſoule, muſt not we that are his members doe the like? But no ſuch <hi>Aſcenſion,</hi> if no <hi>Reſurrection of the body.</hi> Hath not Chriſt promiſed, <hi>That wee ſhall ſit with him at his Table, and eate and drinke with him in his Fathers King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</hi> But no ſuch Eating and Drinking, if no <hi>Reſurrection of the Body.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="214" facs="tcp:170922:113"/>
            <p>When Chriſt in the Goſpel, meant to confute the <hi>Sadducees,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <hi>the Reſurrection,</hi> hee uſed this Argument: Have ye not read, what God ſaid to <hi>Moſes in the Buſh: I am the God of Abraham, the God of Iſaak, and the God of Jakob: God is not the God of the dead, but of the living:</hi> and with this Argument he put them to ſilence. But how their Errour is confuted by this Argument: or how this Argument proves the <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Body,</hi> is not eaſie to bee perceived. It ſeemes, the Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not ſo much <hi>ad Rem,</hi> as <hi>ad Hominem;</hi> though it prove not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly the <hi>Reſurrection of the body,</hi> yet it proves it ſufficiently againſt the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> who therefore denyed the <hi>Reſurrection of the body,</hi> becauſe they beleeved not the <hi>immortality of the ſoule:</hi> and this Argument pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving directly the <hi>immortality of the
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:170922:113"/>ſoule,</hi> proves ſufficiently againſt them, <hi>the Reſurrection of the body.</hi> Or is it, perhaps, meant thus; God is the God of <hi>Abraham;</hi> but <hi>Abraham</hi> is not the ſoule onely, but the whole man: and therefore the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of <hi>Abraham,</hi> though now dead, muſt of neceſſity bee raiſed to life againe; ſeeing, God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, all Morall reaſons, that can be brought to prove the <hi>Immortalitie of the ſoule,</hi> may ſerve as well, to prove the <hi>Reſurrection of the body:</hi> For if there bee reward for the godly in another life; certainely, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhall not bee to the ſoule onely, but as well to the bodie; and if to the body, then muſt the body of neceſſity riſe againe, that it may be capable to receive the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward? But what capacitie, as long as it is lying in the duſt? And as
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:170922:114"/>this reaſon is of force, to prove <hi>the Reſurrection of the body,</hi> in the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: ſo the puniſhment due to ſinne, makes it of no leſſe force, to prove it in the wicked.</p>
            <p>All that hath been ſaid, and all that can be ſaid in this matter; are as ſo many links, that may be made into a chaine, and will neceſſarily draw us on, to this beliefe: For will you except againſt the body, that it is not worthy to bee raiſed from the dead? Or will yee except againſt God, that he is not able to raiſe it from the dead. Or will yee except againſt the cauſe, that it ought not to bee raiſed from the dead; and when all theſe Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are proved unjuſt; what doubt can there bee, of its <hi>riſing from the dead?</hi> For firſt, is not the body worthy to riſe againe; which is, <hi>Vagina afflatus Divini,</hi> the receptacle
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:170922:114"/>and ſheath, as it were, of the Divine breath; and is not our Fleſh, as one cals it <hi>ſoror Chriſti,</hi> the ſiſter of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that if, of it ſelf it be not; at leaſt, by this Conſanguinitie, it is moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. Is not God able to raiſe it againe out of duſt, who at firſt made it of duſt, and duſt of nothing? Is there not juſt cauſe, it ſhould be raiſed againe; indeed ſo juſt, that it is of neceſſitie, if God be juſt. For if the body be not raiſed again, how can it appeare in judgement? And if it appeare not in judgement, how can it receive the ſentence of <hi>Abſolution,</hi> or <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation;</hi> and if it receive not ſuch ſentence, how can it be <hi>Puniſhed,</hi> or <hi>Rewarded,</hi> and if it be not <hi>Puniſhed</hi> or <hi>Rewarded:</hi> how can God bee juſt, that neither puniſheth nor reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, the good or evill it hath done in this life? And ſeeing God is moſt Juſt, even Juſtice it ſe fe. It
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:170922:115"/>followes of neceſſitie, that the Body ſhall be raiſed againe to life: which though it be here made an Article of our Beliefe, for the difficultie; yet it falls within the compaſſe of our knowledge, for the certainty.</p>
            <p>To doubt of the <hi>Reſurrection of the Body,</hi> is to doubt, (as hath been ſaid) of either Gods Power, or of his Will: and to doubt of his Power, is to make him no God: and to doubt of his Will, is to make him not good; For how ſhould he be good, to deſtroy our Bodies, which are <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt;</hi> if hee ſhould not raiſe them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that they may bee Temples for his ſervice? O my ſoule, let this be thy joy for the reſurrection of thy Bodie; Not, that it ſhall riſe againe, to be ſinneful fleſh and bloud as now it is, but that it ſhall riſe to be a Temple for the Holy Ghoſt;
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:170922:115"/>fitted to bee taken into the Quire of Angels, to ſing the praiſes of God, and of his Chriſt for ever. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if I thought my Body ſhould riſe againe, to bee in the ſtate that now it is; though with enjoying as much happineſſe as the world can affoord: yet I would make it my humble ſuit to God, rather to let it lye in the duſt ſtill, then to raiſe it up to ſuch a life. For alas, O Lord, what do the pleaſures of the World, but diſtract mee from thee; and what is my hope, but to enjoy thy preſence? What is the World, but a barre to keepe thee from me: and what contentment can I have, while I am without thee? No my ſoule, thou ſhouldſt do moſt unkindly, to wiſh my Bodies riſing againe; if it were not to bee with God, and to ſerve him as a Temple of his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. For without this, no <hi>Reſurrection
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:170922:116"/>of the body</hi> ſhall be welcome to me; Alas, not ſo good as lying quickly in the duſt.</p>
            <p>But if it were meant, that our Bodies indeed ſhould riſe againe, and be the ſame hereafter, as now they are; why would God ſuffer them to dye at all? and not rather con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue them alive ſtill? For ſo hee might have ſaved himſelfe the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of new making them; and us the miſery, of ſo long miſſing them. But now, ſeeing the ſoule hath beene without its body, ſo many hundred yeares already, and is like to bee without it, God knowes, how many hundred yeares more; why may it not be contented, to be without it altogether, and never ſtand expecting this impoſſible <hi>Reſurrection?</hi> But, O my ſoule, how vaine are theſe thoughts? For what are we, that we ſhould enter into Gods ſecrets? as
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170922:116"/>though wee could comprehend that which is Incomprehenſible; and ſearch out that, which is Unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able? As for Gods ſuffering the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die to die, and not continuing it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live ſtill; who ſees not the reaſon, that knowes the ſentence, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by God upon <hi>Adams</hi> tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion? And as for the Soules wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Body ſo long, who can thinke it long, that conſiders Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity?</p>
            <p>If we did but know, or would but conſider, the admirable won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfulneſſe of the frame of Mans body; we would much more wonder at the Formation of it, then at the Reſurrection of it: and <hi>David</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himſelfe well ſeene in <hi>Anatomie,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>I am wonderfully and fearefully made.</hi> Fearefully made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; For, hee that ſhould looke into the frame of Mans body, and
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:170922:117"/>ſee upon what wonderfull tickle points our life ſtands, might well be afraid; it were not poſſible, wee could live one minute. If then we ſee before our eyes, the great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfulneſſe of the formation of the body: why ſhould we doubt of the leſſe wonderfulneſſe, the <hi>Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the body?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a place in one of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes, where he ſaith, <hi>The Lord keepeth the bones of the juſt; one of them ſhall not bee conſumed;</hi> from which place, the <hi>Jewes</hi> conceive an opinion, that <hi>In Spina dorſi,</hi> in the ridge of a mans backe there is a little bone, which will never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, how long ſoever it lye in the earth; and this little bone, to be as it were, <hi>Semen Reſurrecturi Corporis,</hi> the ſeed out of which the Body ſhall riſe againe: and as God made <hi>Eve</hi> of onely a bone of <hi>Adam,</hi> yet of
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170922:117"/>that bone, he made her bone of his bone, and fleſh of his fleſh: So of this little backe bone, God will raiſe the Body againe, to bee the ſame bones and fleſh it was before. But what need we looke after any ſuch bone; when the leaſt crumme of duſt, is Seed ſufficient for God, to raiſe it up the ſame body it was before. And indeed, we have ſurer ground for our beliefe, then <hi>Jewiſh Fables:</hi> For if wee Beleeve that <hi>Chriſt is riſen from the dead,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt of our owne riſing; ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hee therefore did riſe, that hee might be <hi>Primitiae reſurgentium, The firſt fruits of them that riſe;</hi> but the firſt Fruits he could not be, if others did not riſe as well as hee. And therefore having beleeved in an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle before, that Chriſt roſe from the dead; this Article of our own riſing, is but <hi>Ex Abundanti,</hi> more
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:170922:118"/>then needed; but that the difficulty of beleeving it, requires, as it were, a double Buttreſſe to ſtrengthen our Faith.</p>
            <p>There are ſome perhaps, that look for Naturall reaſons to prove De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively, <hi>the Reſurrection of the body;</hi> but is not their expectation very unjuſt, to expect Naturall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, to prove a thing that is not Naturall? If Naturall reaſons could be given of it, it ſhould be fitter for the <hi>Metaphyſicks,</hi> then a Creed; and as able to breed a Knowledge, as Beliefe: Our Reaſon onely helps us thus farre, to make us know, there is ſomething left for Beliefe, which Reaſon cannot reach to, and of this nature is the <hi>Reſurrection of the body:</hi> our. Beliefe ſhall then be turned into knowledge, when we ſhall come to have experience of it; in the meane time, wee muſt content our ſelves
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:170922:118"/>with Beleeving it: And, O my Soule, doe thou beleeve it indeed; and be moſt aſſured, that though thy Body leave thee for a time, and bee laid in duſt, and bee turned to duſt: yet it will not bee long, ere it ſhall riſe, and bee joyned with thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, as now it is; but in a far hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier condition then now it is: Not ſtubborne and reſtiffe then, but tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctable and obſequious: not earthly and lumpiſh then, but Aery and light; and indeed, ſuch a body it ſhall be, as thou wouldſt wiſh it to be: Not ſubject to diſeaſes, Not weary with labours: Not itching with luſt: Not drowſie with ſleep: Not hungring after meat; and which is moſt of all, where now it takes upon it to be thy Maſter, It ſhall then be content to be thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant; but ſuch a ſervant, as ſhall therefore ſerve thee, becauſe thou
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:170922:119"/>ſerveſt God: <hi>For it is ſowne a Naturall body, it ſhall bee raiſed up a ſpirituall Body: It is ſowne in corruption, it ſhall be rayſed in incorruption;</hi> the ſame body in ſubſtance that now it is, but endued with Spirituall and better qualities.</p>
            <p>Many queſtions are here moved by the Schoolmen; as whether the bodies of Abortives, which were never borne, but dyed in their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombes, ſhall be partakers of <hi>the Reſurrection;</hi> ſeeing, though they never came to ſee the light, yet they had beene once alive and quicke? Then, whether bodies ſhall ariſe, of the ſame age and ſtature, at which they died: as Infants, at the ſtature and age of Infants: and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, at their ſeverall ſtatures and ages; Or elſe ſhall all riſe at a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect age and ſtature; becauſe of the words of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in his Epiſtle
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:170922:119"/>to the <hi>Epheſians, Till we all come unto a perfect man, to the meaſure of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the fulnes of Chriſt.</hi> Then, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bodies ſhall ariſe, with the ſame deformities and defects, which they had living: as, Crooked, Lame, Blinde; or otherwiſe, mutilation of Members: ſeeing Chriſt aroſe, with the ſame wounds which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, when his body was pierced with the Speare? And many ſuch queſtions moved more out of vaine curioſity, then tending to Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and which perhaps may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babably be argued, as having cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours on both ſides: but can never directly be defined, as having war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant on either ſide: Reaſon may make conjectures of it; but Faith will build no certainty on it. It may bee ſufficient for us to beleeve, that the bodies of all men, ſhall riſe at the laſt day, and ſtand at the Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:170922:120"/>of Chriſt, who ſhall come from Heaven, <hi>to judge the Quick and the Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now having beleeved the two Articles, that properly relate to the Sonne of God, Chriſt Jeſus: <hi>[the Forgiveneſſe of ſinnes, and the Reſurrection of the Bodie.]</hi> It fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes fitly, to beleeve the Article, that properly relates to God the Father; <hi>[The life Everlaſting,]</hi> and it followes not onely fitly, but ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neceſſarily: For, if we ſhould not adde, <hi>the life Everlaſting,</hi> it might be thought, that our Reſurrection were but like theirs, who roſe at the time of Chriſts riſing: and appeared to many in the Holy City, who roſe indeede, but then died againe: at leaſt, who can tell what became of them, and ſo our Beliefe ſhould caſt Anchor in a very unſafe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: but now by adding the <hi>life
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:170922:120"/>Everlaſting,</hi> we make the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of our Bodies, a perpetuity; and beleeve they ſhall riſe againe, never any more to dy. And indeed how can it be otherwiſe? ſeeing there never was but one ſentence of death denounced againſt man: and that ſentence once executed, by his dying once: there is no new ſentence of dying any more; and therefore the Body being beleeved, to be raiſed from the dead; the <hi>life Everlaſting</hi> will bee beleeved of courſe. Death indeede is a debt due to nature, and a debt that nature lookes to have payd; but yet na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not ſo unjuſt, to looke that a debt ſhould be payd her more then once: and therefore the body having payd the debt once, by dying once: if it can get to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and live; it will not be then in natures debt any more, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:170922:121"/>cannot naturally dy any more, but ſhall live for ever.</p>
            <p>But why is there no mention made in our Creed, of the Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality of the ſoule? that of this poynt, there might be left no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; for as long as this is in ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, wee ſhall neceſſarily fall into the errour of the <hi>Sadduces;</hi> and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver beleeve the Reſurrection of the body. Is it not, that the Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the ſoule, is therefore not made an Article of our Creed; becauſe it is not ſo properly credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>Per fidem,</hi> as demonſtrable <hi>per artem:</hi> there being ſo apparent rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for it, that even the Heathen themſelves have not denyed it; and one of their owne Poets could ſay:
<q>
                  <hi>Parte tamen meliore mei, ſuper acta perennis Aſtra forar;</hi>
               </q> meaning his ſoule. Beſides, what
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:170922:121"/>need is there of mentioning it, when it is ſufficiently intimated, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded rather, in theſe two laſt Articles. For if we beleeve the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the body, we cannot doubt of the Immortality of the ſoule; ſeeing the body cannot riſe, without the ſoule: and if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve the <hi>life Everlaſting,</hi> we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but beleeve the ſoule to bee Immortall; ſeeing without the ſoule, there can be no life at all.</p>
            <p>And now wee are come to the laſt Article of our Creed, which may well bee the laſt; ſeeing it brings us to that which is <hi>Everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> And here it may not be unfit, to examine a little the extent of this <hi>Everlaſting life:</hi> ſeeing it is not momentary, and fading, as our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent life is; but continuing and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, without having any l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt: that if we ſay, it ſhall laſt a Thouſand
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:170922:122"/>years, if a million of thouſand years, if ſo many millions of thouſand yeares, as there are ſands in the ſea: although an infinite incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible extent of time; yet wee ſhall expreſſe but a very ſmall part, or rather indeed, no part at all of it; ſeeing, of thoſe, how many ſoever, yet they will have an end at laſt; Everlaſtingneſſe, never. It may beſt bee expreſt by number <hi>In ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracto,</hi> of which, when never ſo many have bin preceding; yet never the fewer will bee left behind. O the wonderfulneſſe of everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe! enough to amaze our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: ſo wonderfull, that when wee have wondred as much as we can, wee may begin and wonder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and he that ſhall ſtand won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring all his life long: yet cannot be thought to have wondred e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Iuſtly therefore is it made
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:170922:122"/>an Article of our Creede; ſeeing it exceeds our capacity, it paſſeth our underſtanding, it tranſcends our rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; onely Faith is apprehenſive of it.</p>
            <p>And where is it then, that this E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting life ſhall bee led? Is it not, that of the firſt thouſand years, we may perhaps give ſome account: that it ſhall be led, where wee ſhall reigne with Chriſt; for ſo Saint <hi>John</hi> the Evangeliſt, in plaine termes delivers it: and <hi>Papias</hi> a Biſhop, and a Scholler of Saint <hi>Johns,</hi> who was likely to have learned the meaning of his words, affirmes more; that it ſhall be led heere upon earth, in all delights and pleaſures both of body and minde: and indeede, moſt of the ancient Fathers of that Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive time, runne together by a line in this Expoſition; and yet by the later Fathers, is this Opinion cleane
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:170922:123"/>exploded: and the words of Saint <hi>John</hi> expounded in a farre differing ſenſe, and not without cauſe: for ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is truely ſaid, that <hi>fleſh and bloud ſhal not enter into the kingdom of heaven,</hi> there is no likelihood, that bodily or fleſhly pleaſures ſhall ever be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have place in that kingdome.</p>
            <p>Is it then, that there ſhall be a <hi>new heaven, and a new earth;</hi> and then this life Everlaſting ſhall be led? And it is indeed moſt likely, that as our bodies ſhall riſe, though in their old ſubſtance; yet endued with new qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities: So heaven and earth, where they are to abide, ſhall ſuffer the like alteration; that ſo there may bee a correſpondence between our bodies and them; which could not be, if the qualities of heaven and earth, were not aſwell altered, as of our bodies.</p>
            <p>But when is it that this life Everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſhall beginne? Indeed as ſoone
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:170922:123"/>as this momentary life ſhall end; but yet, but in part: and therefore we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve <hi>the reſurrection of the body,</hi> firſt; and then <hi>the life everlaſting,</hi> after: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, although the ſoule in its kind, be living ſtill; yet till the body riſe againe, there will be no perfect life; and it is not intended, that our life ſhould be <hi>everlaſting,</hi> in the imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of it, which is the ſeparation of the ſoule from the body; but that the body riſing againe, and joyning with the ſoule, it ſhall then bee <hi>everlaſting.</hi> And now my ſoule, conſider the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of our future life, from this that is preſent; which ſhal be ſo much longer then this, as eternity, then a moment; and ſo much better then this, as happineſſe then miſery.</p>
            <p>But wherein ſhall the happineſſe of our future life conſiſt? For if bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily pleaſures be reſtrained, there will want a great part of that, which wee
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:170922:124"/>now count happineſſe. Indeed bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pleaſures will be reſtained, but not pleaſures of the body: but <hi>the body be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing raiſed up a ſpirituall body,</hi> the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures alſo of the body, ſhal be ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all pleaſures. And how much the ſoul is better then the body: how much the reaſon is better then the ſenſe; ſo much ſhall the pleaſures of our future life, bee better then the pleaſures of our preſent life; and if this doe not ſufficiently expreſſe the difference; Remember then how Chriſt hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt it, that the pleaſures of our fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture life ſhall bee ſuch, as <hi>neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man:</hi> and by this, certainely we may well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the infiniteneſs of the difference.</p>
            <p>But what are theſe pleaſures, <hi>which eye hath not ſeene, nor eare hath heard?</hi> Indeed, if wee could tell, vvee ſhould make Chriſts vvords but vaine; yet in
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:170922:124"/>ſome ſort, perhaps, vvee may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them: For vvhat eye hath ſeene the faces of <hi>Cherubins</hi> in their brightneſſe? What eare hath heard the melody of Angels in their ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe? But which is moſt of all, into what heart of man hath it entred, what the glory of the Almighty God is; and what joy it will be to us, to be admitted into his bleſſed preſence? O my ſoule, theſe are pleaſures, which if we could appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend, would drive us into extaſie, at leaſt, would raiſe up our minds from groveling in the baſe pleaſures of this vaine world.</p>
            <p>And who are they that ſhall bee partakers of this life Everlaſting? are they onely the godly; or as well alſo the wicked? Indeed, as well the wicked, as the godly; but not the wicked, ſo well as the godly. For alas, the wicked ſhall live <hi>everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi>
               <pb n="238" facs="tcp:170922:125"/>indeed; if it may bee called life, which is infinitely worſe then any death, to bee in perpetuall torment, and paine inſufferable: Onely the godly ſhall live everlaſtingly; the life which is onely worthy to bee called life; in perpetuall joy, and happineſſe unſpeakable.</p>
            <p>Oh then, if our lives ſhall neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily bee <hi>everlaſting,</hi> and that the happineſſe of the everlaſtingneſſe depends upon this moment we now live. Let us endeavour to ſpend our ſhort time ſo; that our everlaſting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, may be in joy, and not in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery. O my ſoule, be alwaies think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this word <hi>Never:</hi> Never ſhall the torments of the wicked have an end; Never ſhall the joyes of the godly have an end: not after a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, not after a million of yeares, not after a million of milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Ages; but <hi>Never, Never;</hi>
               <pb n="239" facs="tcp:170922:125"/>which if wee could apprehend, or would but conſider; it would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely be a <hi>Remora</hi> to us; and give a ſtop to all our vaine courſes.</p>
            <p>And now having briefly run over theſe Articles of our Creed; we may doe well to conſider, how happy the Church of <hi>God</hi> ſhould be, if it would content it ſelfe with theſe Articles, as once it did: For then the little Barke of Chriſt ſhould not bee toſſed with ſo many tempeſts of <hi>Schiſmes;</hi> ſhould not be torn with ſo many rents of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion as now it is: but ſhould enjoy the unity of faith in the bond of peace: where now, while new Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles are dayly obtruded upon our Conſciences, we ſeem to be in worſe caſe with Articles of faith, then the old <hi>Jewes</hi> were, with the Ceremonies of the Law: they overwhelmed with number, we with novelty, or rather indeed with both.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
